<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
	<link rel="self" href="http://blog.bigdoor24.pl/BigDoorWyamBlog" />
	<id>http://blog.bigdoor24.pl/BigDoorWyamBlog</id>
	<title>BigDoor24 Blog</title>
	<rights>2018</rights>
	<updated>2018-06-13T12:20:23Z</updated>
	<subtitle>Welcome!</subtitle>
	<entry>
		<author>
			<name>Team BigDoor24</name>
		</author>
		<link href="http://blog.bigdoor24.pl/BigDoorWyamBlog/posts/2018-06-12-buying-polish-zloty-do-s-dont-s.html" />
		<link rel="enclosure" type="image" href="http://blog.bigdoor24.pl/BigDoorWyamBlog/assets/Images/europln.jpg" />
		<id>http://blog.bigdoor24.pl/BigDoorWyamBlog/posts/2018-06-12-buying-polish-zloty-do-s-dont-s.html</id>
		<title>Buying Polish Zloty - do's &amp; dont's</title>
		<updated>2018-06-12T14:42:51Z</updated>
		<content>&lt;p&gt;If you are in Poland for the weekend it is unlikely you will spend enough to make any real difference to how you buy your Zloty but for anyone staying a little longer, it's worth figuring out the most efficient way of changing your currency.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;It's all about the spread&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The spread is the difference between what Zloty sells and buys for. For example - EUR/ PLN 4.20 - 4.30 means that the exchange will sell you 4.20 PLN for every 1 Euro and buy your PLN for 1 euro for every PLN 4.30 exchanged.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With this in mind then you don't actually have to know what the current exchange rate is or even the price in another location. The wider the spread, the difference between the two prices , is the best indication of getting best value.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;It is for this reason that it is safe to say that you should never exchange money in any high street bank&lt;/em&gt;. In many instances you will find that, using the above example, their price could be something like 3.90 - 4.70. This is the financial equivalent of punching you in the face when you step inside.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Kantor&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Kantors are littered throughout all Polish cities and they are by far and away the best place to exchange your cash. You should expect a price of 4.25 - 4.30, again using the above example, and sometimes as good as 4.27 - 4.29.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;**Online **&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When you want to transfer money from home it may be best to use one of the dedicated FX platforms like RKantor.com which tends to be quite competitive.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Ask a local&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Because many Poles have their home loans in non-Zloty currencies they are very aware of the best places to exchange their money. It may be best to ask them which particular local Kantors tend to consistently give the best rates.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;The&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Polish Zloty&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It's a well managed and fairly stable currency so you shouldn't expect any large swings. The best advice might be to just change your money when you need to rather than waiting for a better price unless you require a substantial amount changed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hope it helps !&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
		<summary>&lt;p&gt;If you are in Poland for the weekend it is unlikely you will spend enough to make any real difference to how you buy your Zloty but for anyone staying a little longer, it's worth figuring out the most efficient way of changing your currency.&lt;/p&gt;</summary>
	</entry>
	<entry>
		<author>
			<name>Team BigDoor24</name>
		</author>
		<link href="http://blog.bigdoor24.pl/BigDoorWyamBlog/posts/2018-06-12-choosing-a-language-school-things-to-consider.html" />
		<link rel="enclosure" type="image" href="http://blog.bigdoor24.pl/BigDoorWyamBlog/assets/Images/polish-alphabet.png" />
		<id>http://blog.bigdoor24.pl/BigDoorWyamBlog/posts/2018-06-12-choosing-a-language-school-things-to-consider.html</id>
		<title>Choosing a Language School - things to consider</title>
		<updated>2018-06-12T13:06:42Z</updated>
		<content>&lt;p&gt;While it's true that a lot of Poles speak English and in many cases a third language, to really experience the country you may want to learn Polish, or at least enough to get around.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;WHY ?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Before even searching for a suitable course, decide why you want to learn. to become fully proficient can take a lot of time and unless you are interested in adding your name to the history of great Polish literature, a course that concentrates just on conversation may be the best for you.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Obviously recommendations from friends or on social media can help but prices can vary so it's definitely worth looking at a number of schools.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;SIZE MATTERS&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The size of the class can have a real bearing on how fast and how much you learn. While one-to-one classes are the fastest way to learn they are obviously more expensive. A good rule of thumb is the smaller the classes the more effective the course so look for details of what each school guarantees about this before committing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;TEACHING STYLE&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some schools use one style of learning ( i.e. Callan Method ) and others prefer a different style. All will swear by their chosen method but you are your own best guide as to how you learn. Take the time to investigate each schools style and choose the one that best suits you.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;PRICE&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are a lot of language schools in every Polish city so there is lots of competition. Be on the lookout for discounts offered on groupon etc. if you aren't locked in to particular dates. At the same time, invariably the cheaper it is the larger the class size so you will need to decide which is more important.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;EXTRAS&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Does the school do field trips into town to allow you to practice your new polish skills in a real world environment ? What support do they give to slow learners ? Do they require you to buy text books from them at inflated prices or can you by them second hand?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The vast majority of Polish language schools are full of dedicated talented teachers who passionately want to promote their language so wherever you choose you are likely to have a great time and make some new friends in the process.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
		<summary>&lt;p&gt;While it's true that a lot of Poles speak English and in many cases a third language, to really experience the country you may want to learn Polish, or at least enough to get around.&lt;/p&gt;</summary>
	</entry>
	<entry>
		<author>
			<name>Team BigDoor24</name>
		</author>
		<link href="http://blog.bigdoor24.pl/BigDoorWyamBlog/posts/2018-06-12-best-city-for-an-airbnb-investment.html" />
		<link rel="enclosure" type="image" href="http://blog.bigdoor24.pl/BigDoorWyamBlog/assets/Images/airbnb.jpg" />
		<id>http://blog.bigdoor24.pl/BigDoorWyamBlog/posts/2018-06-12-best-city-for-an-airbnb-investment.html</id>
		<title>Best city for an Airbnb Investment</title>
		<updated>2018-06-12T11:44:13Z</updated>
		<content>&lt;p&gt;Everyone is doing it so why can't I ?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you are considering investing in Polish property and renting out with Airbnb, the first issue is location. With the advent of remote check-in, buying where you live is no longer a restraint and optimal returns should drive your decision&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The graph below details expected returns based on a 45 sqm apartment and 100 % occupancy. ( source: Morizon, Airbnb)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="/assets/Images/airbnb-graph.png" class="img-fluid" alt="" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Before you rush off to Bydgoszcz , there are of course other factors that should influence your decision i.e. local management facilities, future property price growth, tourism numbers etc.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Additionally it's hard to argue against Warsaw and Krakow being magnets for visitors to Poland but as our research shows, the obvious is not always the best.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And don't forget, with bigdoor24.pl you not only get automatic discounts in agency fees but also cash back on homeloans.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Happy hunting&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
		<summary>&lt;p&gt;Everyone is doing it so why can't I ?&lt;/p&gt;</summary>
	</entry>
	<entry>
		<author>
			<name>Team BigDoor24</name>
		</author>
		<link href="http://blog.bigdoor24.pl/BigDoorWyamBlog/posts/2018-06-11-where-i-live.html" />
		<link rel="enclosure" type="image" href="http://blog.bigdoor24.pl/BigDoorWyamBlog/assets/Images/crazy-house.jpg" />
		<id>http://blog.bigdoor24.pl/BigDoorWyamBlog/posts/2018-06-11-where-i-live.html</id>
		<title>Where I live</title>
		<updated>2018-06-11T15:51:20Z</updated>
		<content>&lt;p&gt;Can you help your fellow expats (and promote your business/interests for free) ?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you are already living in Poland, please send us details of your area, in English and/or your native language.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An example of the information that would be helpful can be found here&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://bigdoor24.pl/blog/posts/2018-02-12-where-i-live-john-naughton-krakow-rzaska.html"&gt;https://bigdoor24.pl/blog/posts/2018-02-12-where-i-live-john-naughton-krakow-rzaska.html&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Simply email your contribution to&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;easier&amp;#64;bigdoor24.pl&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;and we will do the rest.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Big Thanks !&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
		<summary>&lt;p&gt;Can you help your fellow expats (and promote your business/interests for free) ?&lt;/p&gt;</summary>
	</entry>
	<entry>
		<author>
			<name>BigDoor24 Team</name>
		</author>
		<link href="http://blog.bigdoor24.pl/BigDoorWyamBlog/posts/2018-02-12-where-i-live-john-naughton-krakow-rzaska.html" />
		<link rel="enclosure" type="image" href="http://blog.bigdoor24.pl/BigDoorWyamBlog/assets/Images/rzaskapic.jpg" />
		<id>http://blog.bigdoor24.pl/BigDoorWyamBlog/posts/2018-02-12-where-i-live-john-naughton-krakow-rzaska.html</id>
		<title>Where I Live - Krakow, Rzaska </title>
		<updated>2018-06-10T08:34:33Z</updated>
		<content>&lt;dl class="list-terms-variant-1 text-left"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Name&lt;/dt&gt; 
&lt;dd&gt;John Naughton&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Nationality&lt;/dt&gt; 
&lt;dd&gt;Irish&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;City&lt;/dt&gt; 
&lt;dd&gt;Krakow&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;District &lt;/dt&gt; 
&lt;dd&gt;Rzaska&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Business website&lt;/dt&gt; 
&lt;dd&gt;&lt;a href="https://bigdoor24.pl" target="_blank"&gt;BigDoor24.pl&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Rent or bought and since when?&lt;/dt&gt; 
&lt;dd&gt;Bought in 2017&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Apartment or house?&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;House&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;
&lt;p class="offset-top-16"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What attracted you to the district?&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first thing was the proximity to the train station that brings us directly in to the city , just a few minutes walk from the house.. Really nice neighbours and a quiet environment. We have a  two year old toddler and there is a good infrastructure around to keep her entertained.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Zabierzow is the nearest village with a Tesco and Biedronka.  We are only minutes drive away from Factory and only 10 minutes to Bronowice Galeria so we really aren't far from anything. Without a car, it may be more difficult but there are plenty of bus connections.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Very close to the A4 ring road which gets us out of the city without going through the centre and 10 minutes from the airport is also handy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Any negatives?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Air, The Air , The Air and there are no local bars , none that open after 10 pm anyway.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What are you doing here?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am working with BigDoor24.pl, trying to make life easier for expats living in and planning to visit Poland, and at the same time, teaching  my trilingual toddler that I can't understand all of her new words.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What's your best tip for people looking to buy /rent/get a home loan?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Use BigDoor24.pl !&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Other useful links&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Rz%C4%85ska"&gt;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Rz%C4%85ska&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
		<summary>&lt;p class="offset-top-16"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What attracted you to the district?&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;/p&gt;</summary>
	</entry>
</feed>