<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
	<channel>
		<title>BigDoor24 Blog</title>
		<link>https://bigdoor24.pl/BigDoorWyamBlog</link>
		<description>Welcome!</description>
		<copyright>2018</copyright>
		<pubDate>Tue, 31 Jul 2018 19:53:48 GMT</pubDate>
		<lastBuildDate>Tue, 31 Jul 2018 19:53:48 GMT</lastBuildDate>
		<item>
			<title>Is this the most expensive residential home for sale in Poland today ?</title>
			<link>https://bigdoor24.pl/BigDoorWyamBlog/posts/2018-06-14-is-this-the-most-expensive-residential-home-for-sale-in-poland-today.html</link>
			<description>&lt;p&gt;No doubt the really really expensive properties currently for sale are whispered about amongst the worlds elite and not posted on websites for all to see. But this one is.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
			<author>Team BigDoor24</author>
			<enclosure url="https://bigdoor24.pl/BigDoorWyamBlog/assets/Images/houseexpensive.jpg" length="0" type="image" />
			<guid>https://bigdoor24.pl/BigDoorWyamBlog/posts/2018-06-14-is-this-the-most-expensive-residential-home-for-sale-in-poland-today.html</guid>
			<pubDate>Tue, 24 Jul 2018 08:08:57 GMT</pubDate>
			<content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;No doubt the really really expensive properties currently for sale are whispered about amongst the worlds elite and not posted on websites for all to see. But this one is.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Only 18 km from Krakow center, this is the most expensive purely residential advertised property for sale at the moment in Poland.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Boasting a tennis court ( only 1 ! ) and surrounded by forest, the price tag of PLN 27,000,000 probably puts it out of reach of the average person. With 24 hour security, the property is offered by Crystal House Brokers in Warsaw.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you are interested in buying it, you should know that in addition to your deposit, taxes and costs, expected to be about PLN 5,000000, your mortgage repayment would be expected to be about PLN 120,000 ...per month.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Time to start looking behind the couch !&lt;/p&gt;
</content:encoded>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>(Fake) Media in Poland</title>
			<link>https://bigdoor24.pl/BigDoorWyamBlog/posts/2018-07-24-fake-media-in-poland.html</link>
			<description>&lt;p&gt;OK so the headline was fake ...ish.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
			<author>Team BigDoor24</author>
			<enclosure url="https://bigdoor24.pl/BigDoorWyamBlog/assets/Images/fake-news.jpg" length="0" type="image" />
			<guid>https://bigdoor24.pl/BigDoorWyamBlog/posts/2018-07-24-fake-media-in-poland.html</guid>
			<pubDate>Tue, 24 Jul 2018 07:53:25 GMT</pubDate>
			<content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;OK so the headline was fake ...ish.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Depending on where you are from, the extra costs on top of monthly rent, called &lt;strong&gt;Media&lt;/strong&gt;, can be perfectly understandable or bafflingly complex to navigate.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Beginning with advertised offers, many times the rental amount does not include the extra fees applicable. These fees can include the obvious electricity or water charges to the more opaque building management fees&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Additionally, you may be required to actually call to each utility office and &lt;strong&gt;register&lt;/strong&gt; with them before moving. Of course this must be repeated at the end of the lease to un-register. No small feat if you don't speak Polish but in many cases a good property agent will be happy to help you out with this.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Before even viewing a property we would suggest you &lt;strong&gt;check with the owner&lt;/strong&gt;/agent the expect full monthly price. The obviously cant guarantee the price of utilities but they should be able to give you a good idea.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Things to consider -&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Gas is cheape&lt;/strong&gt;r than electric and many adverts will define this as it can be an important decision factor for locals when renting.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Building Management &lt;strong&gt;fees can vary&lt;/strong&gt; widely but a good rule of thumb is that a new building can be 2/3 times more expensive than old tenement houses so it is recommended that you confirm this at the beginning.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One solution for those who don't need the hassle would be to agree with the landlord an** all-in monthly price** that can be adjusted upon receipt of confirmed utility bills.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is certainly worth discussing with your agent prior to your property search so your budget is kept in line. Nothing fake about that !&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Happy Hunting,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The BigDoor24 Team&lt;/p&gt;
</content:encoded>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Where I live  - Warsaw, Wlochy</title>
			<link>https://bigdoor24.pl/BigDoorWyamBlog/posts/2018-07-04-where-i-live-wlochy-warsaw.html</link>
			<description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Name&lt;/strong&gt;: Thanasis&lt;/p&gt;</description>
			<author>Thanasis</author>
			<enclosure url="https://bigdoor24.pl/BigDoorWyamBlog/assets/Images/wlochy-warsaw.jpg" length="0" type="image" />
			<guid>https://bigdoor24.pl/BigDoorWyamBlog/posts/2018-07-04-where-i-live-wlochy-warsaw.html</guid>
			<pubDate>Wed, 04 Jul 2018 20:52:08 GMT</pubDate>
			<content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Name&lt;/strong&gt;: Thanasis&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Nationality&lt;/strong&gt;: Cypriot&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;City:&lt;/strong&gt; Warsaw&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Distict:&lt;/strong&gt; Stary Włochy&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Accommodation Type:&lt;/strong&gt; Bought apartment in 2017 ,Ground floor with garden&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What attracted you to, and keeps you in, the district?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It's like leaving Warsaw. Low density housing and lots of greenery are particularly special. Despite being 10km from the centre, the area is well developed and maintained and there are excellent transport links.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We feel lucky living here as we are close to anything we need and my sons school is just a 10-minute drive away, once you leave around 7 a.m.!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Shoppingwise, we are close enough to Popularna and we have Tesco, Pharmacies, Gastorama, Papugarnia and 2 parks nearby( one park being the best in Warsaw).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dom Kulture is also on our corner. There is a Zabka and a 24/7 store within walking distance. and we are also close to Blue City.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To me and my family the entire area allows us to relax as children can play in a safe environment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Any negatives?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Traffic !&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What are you doing here?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am an IT support specialist and automation developer for a very good company here in Warsaw. Additionally, I write blogs for &lt;a href="https://tourspoland.com/blog"&gt;https://tourspoland.com/blog&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What's your best tip for people looking to buy /rent/get a home loan?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;BigDoor24.pl looks like a good idea.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Other useful links&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/W%C5%82ochy"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/W%C5%82ochy&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And -&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For those interested in Warsaw, what to see and  recommendations Thanasis has written the following blog posts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(I hope soon to find time to translate them into Greek- Thanasis)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://tourspoland.com/blog/places-outside-warsaw"&gt;https://tourspoland.com/blog/places-outside-warsaw&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://tourspoland.com/blog/things-to-do-warsaw-with-kids"&gt;https://tourspoland.com/blog/things-to-do-warsaw-with-kids&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://tourspoland.com/blog/warsaw-breakfast"&gt;https://tourspoland.com/blog/warsaw-breakfast&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://tourspoland.com/blog/transport-guide-for-warsaw-poland"&gt;https://tourspoland.com/blog/transport-guide-for-warsaw-poland&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://tourspoland.com/blog/free-museums-warsaw"&gt;https://tourspoland.com/blog/free-museums-warsaw&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
</content:encoded>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>English Language Media in Poland</title>
			<link>https://bigdoor24.pl/BigDoorWyamBlog/posts/2018-06-14-english-language-media-in-poland.html</link>
			<description>&lt;p&gt;Just a few news sources we recommend for the English speakers amongst us.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
			<author>Team BigDoor24</author>
			<enclosure url="https://bigdoor24.pl/BigDoorWyamBlog/assets/Images/newspapers.jpg" length="0" type="image" />
			<guid>https://bigdoor24.pl/BigDoorWyamBlog/posts/2018-06-14-english-language-media-in-poland.html</guid>
			<pubDate>Thu, 14 Jun 2018 15:12:05 GMT</pubDate>
			<content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;Just a few news sources we recommend for the English speakers amongst us.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(Note - If you believe we have missed some, please let us now and we'll be happy to update)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;National&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://thenews.pl"&gt;http://thenews.pl&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.inyourpocket.com/poland"&gt;https://www.inyourpocket.com/poland&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.inyourpocket.com/poland"&gt;http://poland-today.pl&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Warsaw&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.warsawvoice.pl"&gt;http://www.warsawvoice.pl&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://wbj.pl"&gt;http://wbj.pl&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Krakow&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://krakcast.podbean.com/"&gt;https://krakcast.podbean.com/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.krakowpost.com"&gt;http://www.krakowpost.com&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Wroclaw&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://wroclawuncut.com"&gt;http://wroclawuncut.com&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Lodz&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://lodzpost.com"&gt;http://lodzpost.com&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</content:encoded>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Home or Investment - Don't ignore the secondary market</title>
			<link>https://bigdoor24.pl/BigDoorWyamBlog/posts/2018-06-14-home-or-investment-buy-in-the-secondary-market.html</link>
			<description>&lt;p&gt;Case Study&lt;/p&gt;</description>
			<author>Team BigDoor24</author>
			<enclosure url="https://bigdoor24.pl/BigDoorWyamBlog/assets/Images/treehouse.jpg" length="0" type="image" />
			<guid>https://bigdoor24.pl/BigDoorWyamBlog/posts/2018-06-14-home-or-investment-buy-in-the-secondary-market.html</guid>
			<pubDate>Thu, 14 Jun 2018 10:55:44 GMT</pubDate>
			<content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;Case Study&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Recently our attention was drawn to a 7 year old detached house on 6 ars (600sqm) of land which was for sale at a lower price than the new development next door of semi-detached houses on 3 ars..&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The purchase price, fit out costs and financing costs of the adjacent new development, ignoring all the personal time involved, far surpassed the cost of buying what was a perfectly modern detached house with little to refurbish.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So what's going on ?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Firstly, it is an accepted truth of the market that most buyers prefer to buy new properties. It may be because of the historical lack of good quality properties available from the secondary market or people just prefer to have their own style and stamp on their home. Older buildings come with unknown problems and restrictions, particularly those in Tenements.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But there has already been a lot of development in Poland in the last twenty years and from our view, properties in the secondary market show some real value opportunities.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Bizarrely, houses, fully furnished with a planted garden are offered for less than similar properties that require extra time and money before moving in. We believe this will change, maybe not next year, but soon, as more and more high standard secondary properties come on the market and people simply don't have the time required anymore to manage fit-outs etc.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So whether investing or buying a home, keep a keen eye out for properties in the secondary market, you may not have a lot of competition right now.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And remember, the moment you buy a new property , it automatically becomes a secondary market asset.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Happy hunting !&lt;/p&gt;
</content:encoded>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Getting a Property Valuation</title>
			<link>https://bigdoor24.pl/BigDoorWyamBlog/posts/2018-06-13-getting-a-property-valuation.html</link>
			<description>&lt;p&gt;Whether buying or selling, it's a good idea (and required if getting a home loan) to get a good independent valuation. And strangely, not all valuers are created equally.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
			<author>Team BigDoor24</author>
			<enclosure url="https://bigdoor24.pl/BigDoorWyamBlog/assets/Images/housemoney.jpg" length="0" type="image" />
			<guid>https://bigdoor24.pl/BigDoorWyamBlog/posts/2018-06-13-getting-a-property-valuation.html</guid>
			<pubDate>Wed, 13 Jun 2018 13:36:39 GMT</pubDate>
			<content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;Whether buying or selling, it's a good idea (and required if getting a home loan) to get a good independent valuation. And strangely, not all valuers are created equally.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;**You are selling **&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Whilst you don't&amp;quot; need &amp;quot; a valuation it can be difficult to decide on the optimum price to sell for. Your agent will advise a price that they believe will get you to offer the property exclusively through them. This is their first goal and they know they can change the price later.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Looking at other nearby properties for sale on a search engine may help for standard apartments but for houses with gardens etc  it may be harder to judge.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another advantage to getting a valuation is that it can help with negotiations. The banks take the valuation to calculate the home loan so a buyer cannot negotiate too far away from the price by claiming that they only have X to pay etc.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you ensure that the valuer that you hire is accepted by ALL banks you may be able to sell the valuation report to the eventual buyer to use when applying for their home loan.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;**You are buying **&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you are getting a home loan then you will definitely need a valuation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first rule is that you should get a valuer that is accepted by all banks. Some valuers are only accepted by some banks and not others despite having the same qualifications. Your application for a home loan will probably go to more than one bank so this is very very important.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is unlikely that you will get a valuation on every house you view but knowing how much you can borrow will be determined by this report so it's a little bit chicken and egg.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you are unhappy with the valuation feel free to argue. The reports are pretty detailed but there may be some overlooked aspects that you can point out.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Cost&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Costs of valuations can vary wildly depending on the property etc so it is worth shopping around. Obviously the ones that are accepted by all banks are more expensive but at the same time, may save you money down the line.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Where to find them&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The best place is through your Home Loan Advisor rather than a real estate agent. The valuation is to get a homeloan and the mortgage adviser wants you to get one so they should recommend the most suitable professional for your needs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Don't forget that through a BigDoor24.pl referred Home Loan Advisor you will receive cash back which could cover the costs of any valuation professional you hire.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Happy Hunting&lt;/p&gt;
</content:encoded>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Renting without an Agent -  A Checklist</title>
			<link>https://bigdoor24.pl/BigDoorWyamBlog/posts/2018-06-13-renting-without-an-agent-a-checklist.html</link>
			<description>&lt;p&gt;When renting a property through an agent you will normally pay a fee equivalent to one months rent ( or less if using BigDoor24 ).so you may decide you would like to avoid paying anything.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
			<author>Team BigDoor24</author>
			<enclosure url="https://bigdoor24.pl/BigDoorWyamBlog/assets/Images/rent-on-your-own.jpg" length="0" type="image" />
			<guid>https://bigdoor24.pl/BigDoorWyamBlog/posts/2018-06-13-renting-without-an-agent-a-checklist.html</guid>
			<pubDate>Wed, 13 Jun 2018 12:00:27 GMT</pubDate>
			<content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;When renting a property through an agent you will normally pay a fee equivalent to one months rent ( or less if using BigDoor24 ).so you may decide you would like to avoid paying anything.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here are some pointers in how you can go about it&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Finding a property&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You will need to only deal with owners who are offering their properties directly and the best way to find them is by using the filter &amp;quot; owners only &amp;quot; on the property search engine you are using (i.e. Morizon.pl, Otodom.pl, Gratka.pl etc).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Alternatively you can look at gumtree.pl for direct offers from owners or post what you are looking for on one of the local Facebook groups.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You should be aware that this will severely limit the number of properties available to you as the large majority are offered through agencies but you may get lucky.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Negotiating&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is likely that the owner may not speak your language so it would be best to bring a Polish friend or hire a translator while you are negotiating the terms. The additional costs will include electricity, water etc ( called Media ) and building management fees.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Time to sign&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Your agreement will probably be in Polish only and it is a legal document so again , bring a friend or hire a translator. You may also want the Landlord to accompany you to the city registration office to record that you are living there,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is a rare issue but you should also ensure that the landlord is actually the owner of the property. Ask them to bring along ownership documents for you to view before signing..&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Rental agreements are normally pretty standard but if you are wary of any of the terms, bring it to a lawyer to check it over before signing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Upon Signing&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You will be expected to pay your deposit of one month rent and the first month in advance. Additionally you will have to bring your signed lease to the different utility offices to put your name on the relevant electricity, water bills etc.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Agents have a legal responsibility for any property they negotiate on so you won't have this guarantee but you will have saved the fee less any legal and translator charges you incur.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Happy Hunting !&lt;/p&gt;
</content:encoded>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Buying Polish Zloty - do's &amp; dont's</title>
			<link>https://bigdoor24.pl/BigDoorWyamBlog/posts/2018-06-12-buying-polish-zloty-do-s-dont-s.html</link>
			<description>&lt;p&gt;If you are in Poland for the weekend it is unlikely you will spend enough to make any real difference to how you buy your Zloty but for anyone staying a little longer, it's worth figuring out the most efficient way of changing your currency.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
			<author>Team BigDoor24</author>
			<enclosure url="https://bigdoor24.pl/BigDoorWyamBlog/assets/Images/fx-pic.jpg" length="0" type="image" />
			<guid>https://bigdoor24.pl/BigDoorWyamBlog/posts/2018-06-12-buying-polish-zloty-do-s-dont-s.html</guid>
			<pubDate>Tue, 12 Jun 2018 14:42:51 GMT</pubDate>
			<content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;If you are in Poland for the weekend it is unlikely you will spend enough to make any real difference to how you buy your Zloty but for anyone staying a little longer, it's worth figuring out the most efficient way of changing your currency.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;It's all about the spread&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The spread is the difference between what Zloty sells and buys for. For example - EUR/ PLN 4.20 - 4.30 means that the exchange will sell you 4.20 PLN for every 1 Euro and buy your PLN for 1 euro for every PLN 4.30 exchanged.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With this in mind then you don't actually have to know what the current exchange rate is or even the price in another location. The wider the spread, the difference between the two prices , is the best indication of getting best value.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;It is for this reason that it is safe to say that you should never exchange money in any high street bank&lt;/em&gt;. In many instances you will find that, using the above example, their price could be something like 3.90 - 4.70. This is the financial equivalent of punching you in the face when you step inside.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Kantor&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Kantors are littered throughout all Polish cities and they are by far and away the best place to exchange your cash. You should expect a price of 4.25 - 4.30, again using the above example, and sometimes as good as 4.27 - 4.29.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;_Online _&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When you want to transfer money from home it may be best to use one of the dedicated FX platforms like RKantor.com which tends to be quite competitive.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Ask a local&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Because many Poles have their home loans in non-Zloty currencies they are very aware of the best places to exchange their money. It may be best to ask them which particular local Kantors tend to consistently give the best rates.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt; &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Polish Zloty&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It's a well managed and fairly stable currency so you shouldn't expect any large swings. The best advice might be to just change your money when you need to rather than waiting for a better price unless you require a substantial amount changed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Happy Hunting !&lt;/p&gt;
</content:encoded>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Choosing a Language School - things to consider</title>
			<link>https://bigdoor24.pl/BigDoorWyamBlog/posts/2018-06-12-choosing-a-language-school-things-to-consider.html</link>
			<description>&lt;p&gt;While it's true that a lot of Poles speak English and in many cases a third language, to really experience the country you may want to learn Polish, or at least enough to get around.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
			<author>Team BigDoor24</author>
			<enclosure url="https://bigdoor24.pl/BigDoorWyamBlog/assets/Images/polish-alphabet.png" length="0" type="image" />
			<guid>https://bigdoor24.pl/BigDoorWyamBlog/posts/2018-06-12-choosing-a-language-school-things-to-consider.html</guid>
			<pubDate>Tue, 12 Jun 2018 13:06:42 GMT</pubDate>
			<content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;While it's true that a lot of Poles speak English and in many cases a third language, to really experience the country you may want to learn Polish, or at least enough to get around.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;WHY ?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Before even searching for a suitable course, decide why you want to learn. to become fully proficient can take a lot of time and unless you are interested in adding your name to the history of great Polish literature, a course that concentrates just on conversation may be the best for you.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Obviously recommendations from friends or on social media can help but prices can vary so it's definitely worth looking at a number of schools.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;SIZE MATTERS&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The size of the class can have a real bearing on how fast and how much you learn. While one-to-one classes are the fastest way to learn they are obviously more expensive. A good rule of thumb is the smaller the classes the more effective the course so look for details of what each school guarantees class size before committing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;TEACHING STYLE&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some schools use one style of learning ( i.e. Callan Method ) and others prefer a different style. All will swear by their chosen method but you are your own best guide as to how you learn. Take the time to investigate each schools style and choose the one that best suits you.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;PRICE&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are a lot of language schools in every Polish city so there is lots of competition. Be on the lookout for discounts offered on groupon etc. if you aren't locked in to particular dates. At the same time, invariably the cheaper it is the larger the class size so you will need to decide which is more important.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;EXTRAS&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Does the school do field trips into town to allow you to practice your new polish skills in a real world environment ? What support do they give to slow learners ? Do they require you to buy text books from them at inflated prices or can you by them second hand?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The vast majority of Polish language schools are full of dedicated talented teachers who passionately want to promote their language so wherever you choose you are likely to have a great time and make some new friends in the process.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Happy Hunting !&lt;/p&gt;
</content:encoded>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Best city for an Airbnb Investment Q II 2018</title>
			<link>https://bigdoor24.pl/BigDoorWyamBlog/posts/2018-06-12-best-city-for-an-airbnb-investment.html</link>
			<description>&lt;p&gt;Everyone is doing it so why can't I?&lt;/p&gt;</description>
			<author>Team BigDoor24</author>
			<enclosure url="https://bigdoor24.pl/BigDoorWyamBlog/assets/Images/airbnb.jpg" length="0" type="image" />
			<guid>https://bigdoor24.pl/BigDoorWyamBlog/posts/2018-06-12-best-city-for-an-airbnb-investment.html</guid>
			<pubDate>Tue, 12 Jun 2018 11:44:13 GMT</pubDate>
			<content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;Everyone is doing it so why can't I?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you are considering investing in Polish property and renting out with Airbnb, the first issue is location. With the advent of remote check-in, buying where you live is no longer a restraint and optimal returns should drive your decision&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The graph below details expected returns based on a 45sqm apartment and 100% occupancy. ( source: Morizon, Airbnb)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="../assets/Images/airbnb-graph.png" class="img-fluid img-responsive" alt="" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Before you rush off to Bydgoszcz, there are of course other factors that should influence your decision i.e. local management facilities, future property price growth, tourism numbers etc.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Additionally it's hard to argue against Warsaw and Krakow being magnets for visitors to Poland but as our research shows, the obvious is not always the best.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And don't forget, with bigdoor24.pl you not only get automatic discounts in agency fees but also cash back on homeloans.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For updates on this and other property related statistics, &lt;a href="https://www.facebook.com/bigdoor24"&gt;follow us now on Facebook&lt;/a&gt; &lt;div class="fb-follow" data-href="https://www.facebook.com/bigdoor24/" data-layout="standard" data-size="large" data-show-faces="true"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Happy hunting !&lt;/p&gt;
</content:encoded>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Where I Live</title>
			<link>https://bigdoor24.pl/BigDoorWyamBlog/posts/2018-06-11-where-i-live.html</link>
			<description>&lt;p&gt;Can you help your fellow expats (and promote your business/interests for free) ?&lt;/p&gt;</description>
			<author>Team BigDoor24</author>
			<enclosure url="https://bigdoor24.pl/BigDoorWyamBlog/assets/Images/crazy-house.jpg" length="0" type="image" />
			<guid>https://bigdoor24.pl/BigDoorWyamBlog/posts/2018-06-11-where-i-live.html</guid>
			<pubDate>Mon, 11 Jun 2018 15:51:20 GMT</pubDate>
			<content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;Can you help your fellow expats (and promote your business/interests for free) ?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you are already living in Poland, please send us details of your area, in English and/or your native language.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An example of the information that would be helpful can be found here&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://bigdoor24.pl/blog/posts/2018-02-12-where-i-live-john-naughton-krakow-rzaska.html"&gt;https://bigdoor24.pl/blog/posts/2018-02-12-where-i-live-john-naughton-krakow-rzaska.html&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Simply email your contribution to&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;easier&amp;#64;bigdoor24.pl&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;and we will do the rest.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Big Thanks !&lt;/p&gt;
</content:encoded>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Where I Live - Krakow,Suburb West </title>
			<link>https://bigdoor24.pl/BigDoorWyamBlog/posts/2018-02-12-where-i-live-john-naughton-krakow-rzaska.html</link>
			<description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Name&lt;/strong&gt; John N..&lt;/p&gt;</description>
			<author>BigDoor24 Team</author>
			<enclosure url="https://bigdoor24.pl/BigDoorWyamBlog/assets/Images/rzaskapic.jpg" length="0" type="image" />
			<guid>https://bigdoor24.pl/BigDoorWyamBlog/posts/2018-02-12-where-i-live-john-naughton-krakow-rzaska.html</guid>
			<pubDate>Sun, 10 Jun 2018 08:34:33 GMT</pubDate>
			<content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Name&lt;/strong&gt; John N..&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Nationality&lt;/strong&gt; Irish&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;City&lt;/strong&gt; Krakow&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;District&lt;/strong&gt; Zabierzow, Rzaska&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;**Business Website **BigDoor24.pl&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Rent/Bought/Since&lt;/strong&gt; Bought in 2017&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Apartment or House&lt;/strong&gt; House&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What attracted you to, and keeps you in, the district?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first thing was the proximity to the train station that brings us directly in to the city, just a few minutes walk from the house.. Really nice neighbours and a quiet environment. We have a  two year old toddler and there is a good infrastructure around to keep her entertained.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Additionally, our proximity to the the Krakow Business Park means lots of choice for lunch venues.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Zabierzow is the nearest village with a Tesco and Biedronka.  We are only minutes drive away from Factory and only 10 minutes to Bronowice Galeria so we really aren't far from anything. Without a car, it may be more difficult but there are plenty of bus connections.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Very close to the A4 ring road which gets us out of the city without going through the centre and 10 minutes from the airport is also handy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Being 8 KM from the centre means late night beers require a taxi service and we find the best option outside of Uber is iCar or EkoTaxi, much cheaper than other more well known cab companies.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Any negatives?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Air, The Air , The Air and there are no local bars , none that open after 10 pm anyway.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What are you doing here?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am working with BigDoor24.pl, trying to make life easier for expats living in and planning to visit Poland, and at the same time, teaching  my trilingual toddler that I can't understand all of her new words.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What's your best tip for people looking to buy /rent/get a home loan?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Use BigDoor24.pl !&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Other useful links&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Rz%C4%85ska"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Rz%C4%85ska&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</content:encoded>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>When &amp; How to apply for a Home Loan</title>
			<link>https://bigdoor24.pl/BigDoorWyamBlog/posts/2018-06-15-getting-a-home-loan.html</link>
			<description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Tip 1 . It costs nothing to apply so do it early&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
			<author>Team BigDoor24</author>
			<enclosure url="https://bigdoor24.pl/BigDoorWyamBlog/assets/Images/chicken-egg.jpg" length="0" type="image" />
			<guid>https://bigdoor24.pl/BigDoorWyamBlog/posts/2018-06-15-getting-a-home-loan.html</guid>
			<pubDate>Fri, 11 May 2018 06:59:25 GMT</pubDate>
			<content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Tip 1 . It costs nothing to apply so do it early&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You are looking to buy a property but will require a home loan. Well, before you even start looking the first thing you should do is to find out how much you can borrow. Seems obvious but lots of people leave this too late and find themselves rushing with applications at the last moment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Tip 2 - You don't need a hard Home Loan offer but you should have a ballpark idea before you begin&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It can all be a little chicken and egg as the bank will not confirm how much until they know about the property and of course you don't know which property until you know how much you can borrow.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Obviously, signing a preliminary agreement with the seller and paying the non-refundable 10 % deposit can be daunting without an actual guarantee from the bank so do what you can now to avoid this predicament.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Tip 3 - Don't apply to all banks yourself, it may damage your borrowing ability&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It's a long time since relationships between a bank and their customer had any importance and these days it is a simple numbers game so applying to every bank would seem to make more sense. But did you know that this can currently hurt your chances of  success?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At present, the rating agency used by all banks will reduce your credit rating if you are seen to apply to more than three banks, Daft, I know, but there you go.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Tip 4 - Use a qualified professional Advisor - they're free and can only help&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This makes it even more important that you employ the services of a qualified independent Credit Advisor.  They earn commission from the bank so there is no charge to you for their work. A good Advisor should be able to assess your situation quickly and give you good guidance on how much you can expect to borrow. Additionally they will also be aware of which banks would be more interested in lending to you, thus increasing your chances of success.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Tip 5 - Be aware of the ancillary costs when budgeting&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When budgeting, be sure to include the valuation and arrangement fees that can be anywhere between 1-2 % of the loan amount.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Tip 6 - Not using BigDoor24 can actually cost you money !&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And don't forget, by requesting contact with an Advisor through BigDoor24, you will receive cashback once your loan is confirmed. ( i.e PLN 200 per PLN 100k borrowed  - For more information see FAQ  &lt;a href="https://bigdoor24.pl/Home/FAQ"&gt;https://bigdoor24.pl/Home/FAQ&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is not an offer you will get by going direct.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Happy Hunting !&lt;/p&gt;
</content:encoded>
		</item>
	</channel>
</rss>