<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
	<id>https://bigdoor24.pl/BigDoorWyamBlog</id>
	<title>BigDoor24 Blog</title>
	<link rel="self" href="https://bigdoor24.pl/BigDoorWyamBlog" />
	<rights>2019</rights>
	<updated>2019-11-16T18:32:49Z</updated>
	<subtitle>Welcome!</subtitle>
	<entry>
		<id>https://bigdoor24.pl/BigDoorWyamBlog/posts/2019-11-14-getting-a-property-valuation.html</id>
		<title>Getting a Property Valuation</title>
		<author>
			<name>Team BigDoor24</name>
		</author>
		<link href="https://bigdoor24.pl/BigDoorWyamBlog/posts/2019-11-14-getting-a-property-valuation.html" />
		<link rel="enclosure" type="image" href="https://bigdoor24.pl/assets/Images/valuation-of-home.jpg" />
		<updated>2019-11-14T11:30:29Z</updated>
		<content>&lt;p&gt;Whether buying or selling, it's a good idea (and required if getting a Polish mortgage) to get a good independent valuation. And strangely, not all valuers are created equally.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;You are Selling&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Whilst you don't &amp;quot;need&amp;quot; a valuation, it can be difficult to decide on the optimum price to sell for. Your agent will advise a price that they believe will get you to offer the property exclusively through them. This is their first goal and they know they can change the price later.( We note the better agents realise this is self defeating and should be more market based in their appraisal)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Looking at other nearby properties for sale on a search engine may help for standard apartments but for houses with gardens etc  it may be harder to judge.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another advantage to getting a valuation is that it can help with negotiations. The banks take the valuation to calculate the home loan so a buyer cannot negotiate too far away from the price by claiming that they only have X to pay etc.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you ensure that the valuer that you hire is accepted by ALL banks you may be able to sell the valuation report to the eventual buyer to use when applying for their home loan.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;You are Buying&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you are getting a Polish mortgage then you will definitely need a valuation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first rule is that you should get a valuer that is accepted by all banks. Some valuers are only accepted by some banks and not others despite having the same qualifications. Your application for a home loan will probably go to more than one bank so this is very very important.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is unlikely that you will get a valuation on every house you view but knowing how much you can borrow will be determined by this report so it's a little bit chicken and egg.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you are unhappy with the valuation feel free to argue. The reports are pretty detailed but there may be some overlooked aspects that you can point out.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://bigdoor24.pl/"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Did you know ?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://bigdoor24.pl/"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;BigDoor24.pl sends you a zl. 250 retail voucher of your choice for every successful Polish Mortgage Applicant referred - (in addition to what we send them) - register now for your personal referral code.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Cost&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Costs of valuations can vary wildly depending on the property etc so it is worth shopping around. Obviously the ones that are accepted by all banks are more expensive but at the same time, may save you money down the line. A good indication is anywhere between Zl. 500 and Zl. 1,000 depending on size etc..&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Where to find them&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The best place is through your Polish Mortgage Advisor rather than a real estate agent. The valuation is to get a mortgage and the mortgage adviser wants you to get one so they should recommend the most suitable professional for your needs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Don't forget that through a BigDoor24.pl referred Polish Mortgage Advisor you will receive cash back which could cover the costs of any valuation professional you hire. &lt;a href="https://www.facebook.com/bigdoor24/"&gt;Like us on Facebook for regular helpful articles on living &amp;amp; working in Poland.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Happy Hunting&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Team BigDoor24&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;About BigDoor24.pl&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://bigdoor24.pl/"&gt;
Bigdoor24.pl is a new free service for Expats, finding Property experts who speak your language, securing Commission Discounts &amp;amp; Paying You CashBack on successful Polish mortgage applications. We pay zl. 250 for successful applicant referrals as well as paying the applicant a Zl. 200 for every Zl. 100k borrowed. Register now for details.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
		<summary>&lt;p&gt;Whether buying or selling, it's a good idea (and required if getting a Polish mortgage) to get a good independent valuation. And strangely, not all valuers are created equally.&lt;/p&gt;</summary>
	</entry>
	<entry>
		<id>https://bigdoor24.pl/BigDoorWyamBlog/posts/2019-11-14-buying-selling-polish-zloty-dos-donts.html</id>
		<title>Buying &amp; Selling Polish Zloty - Do's &amp; Dont's</title>
		<author>
			<name>Team BigDoor24</name>
		</author>
		<link href="https://bigdoor24.pl/BigDoorWyamBlog/posts/2019-11-14-buying-selling-polish-zloty-dos-donts.html" />
		<link rel="enclosure" type="image" href="https://bigdoor24.pl/assets/Images/fx-in-poland.jpg" />
		<updated>2019-11-14T10:10:29Z</updated>
		<content>&lt;p&gt;If you are in Poland for the weekend it is unlikely you will spend enough to make any real difference to how you buy your Zloty but for anyone staying a little longer, it's worth figuring out the most efficient way of changing your currency.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;It's all about the spread&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The spread is the difference between what Zloty sells and buys for. For example - EUR/ PLN 4.20 - 4.30 means that the exchange will sell you 4.20 PLN for every 1 Euro and buy your PLN for 1 Euro for every PLN 4.30 exchanged.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With this in mind then you don't actually have to know what the current exchange rate is or even the price in another location. The smaller the spread, the difference between the two prices, is the best indication of getting best value.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;It is for this reason that it is safe to say that you should never exchange money in any high street bank&lt;/em&gt;. In many instances you will find that, using the above example, their price could be something like 3.90 - 4.70. This is the financial equivalent of punching you in the face when you step inside.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://bigdoor24.pl/"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Did you know ?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://bigdoor24.pl/"&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;BigDoor24.pl sends you a zl. 250 retail voucher of your choice for every successful Polish Mortgage Applicant referred - (in addition to what we send them) - register now for your personal referral code.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Kantor - FX Money Exchange Store&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Kantors are littered throughout all Polish cities and they are by far and away the best place to exchange your cash. You should expect a price of 4.25 - 4.30, again using the above example, and sometimes as good as 4.27 - 4.29.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;**&lt;em&gt;Online&lt;/em&gt; **&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When you want to transfer money from home it may be best to use one of the dedicated FX platforms like &lt;a href="https://www.rkantor.com/"&gt;RKantor.com&lt;/a&gt; which tends to be quite competitive.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Cards&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Using cards like &lt;a href="https://www.revolut.com/en-PL?p=branded_campaign&amp;amp;ext=&amp;amp;gclid=EAIaIQobChMIieaWkb3p5QIVxpQYCh3hUgA9EAAYASAAEgJRaPD_BwE"&gt;Revolut&lt;/a&gt;  or &lt;a href="https://n26.com/en-eu/euro-bank-account?utm_source=google&amp;amp;utm_medium=br&amp;amp;utm_campaign=1617329946&amp;amp;utm_content=62689487418&amp;amp;utm_term=n26&amp;amp;matchtype=e&amp;amp;device=c&amp;amp;loc_physical_ms=9067602&amp;amp;gclid=EAIaIQobChMI9bT-gb7p5QIVBqqaCh0CgwM0EAAYASAAEgJ1m_D_BwE"&gt;N26&lt;/a&gt; claim to take away a lot of the hassle with good value currency transfers built in.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Ask a local&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Because many Poles have their home loans in non-Zloty currencies they are very aware of the best places to exchange their money. It may be best to ask them which particular local Kantors or online services tend to consistently give the best rates.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;The&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Polish Zloty&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It's a well managed and fairly stable currency so you shouldn't expect any large swings. The best advice might be to just change your money when you need to rather than waiting for a better price unless you require a substantial amount changed. If you do require a larger amount changed or you are planning a Polish Mortgage in a currency other than Zloty, speak to your bank (make sure they are giving you a good rate, not always applicable) or use an online service.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;ATM&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unless you are desperate but really .. just don't. The rate of exchange, particularly at the Euro ATM's, are close to criminal.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Happy Hunting !&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Team BigDoor24&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;About BigDoor24.pl&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://bigdoor24.pl/"&gt;
Bigdoor24.pl is a new free service for Expats, finding Property experts who speak your language, securing Commission Discounts &amp;amp; Paying You CashBack on successful Polish mortgage applications. We pay zl. 250 for successful applicant referrals as well as paying the applicant a Zl. 200 for every Zl. 100k borrowed. Register now for details.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
		<summary>&lt;p&gt;If you are in Poland for the weekend it is unlikely you will spend enough to make any real difference to how you buy your Zloty but for anyone staying a little longer, it's worth figuring out the most efficient way of changing your currency.&lt;/p&gt;</summary>
	</entry>
	<entry>
		<id>https://bigdoor24.pl/BigDoorWyamBlog/posts/2019-11-10-the-digest-10th-november-2019.html</id>
		<title>The Digest - 10th November 2019</title>
		<author>
			<name>Team BigDoor24</name>
		</author>
		<link href="https://bigdoor24.pl/BigDoorWyamBlog/posts/2019-11-10-the-digest-10th-november-2019.html" />
		<link rel="enclosure" type="image" href="https://bigdoor24.pl/assets/Images/digest-10nov.jpg" />
		<updated>2019-11-10T07:41:00Z</updated>
		<content>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Today the Shops are CLOSED&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The above picture is how the Polish Nation was drawn up after the Versailles Conference post WW1&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Polish Nationhood/ Warsaw - New Traffic Cop Powers/ Poznan - Easy Tiger/ Krakow - Bagatella Sex Abuse/Tri-City - $3 Billion for Port/ Wroclaw - Strip Club Death/ Islamophobia in Poland/ Polish WADA Head/ TikTok Teen/ Versailles Treaty Podcast and more&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.facebook.com/bigdoor24/"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;If you enjoy The Digest please support and Like us on Facebook, posted every Sunday at 10 am and share to your favourite FB groups now.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="sharethis-inline-share-buttons"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;National&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.thefirstnews.com/article/how-poland-became-a-nation-again-after-wwi"&gt;How Poland became a Nation after WW1&lt;/a&gt; - FirstNews&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Local&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Warsaw&lt;/em&gt; -&lt;a href="https://www.tvn24.pl/tvn24-news-in-english,157,m/polish-customs-intercept-8-5-kilo-of-heroin-at-warsaw-chopin-airport,976416.html"&gt; &lt;/a&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.tvn24.pl/tvn24-news-in-english,157,m/polish-police-has-more-powers-when-conducting-road-stops,984018.html"&gt;New Police Traffic Powers&lt;/a&gt; - TVN (Video)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Poznan -&lt;/em&gt; &lt;a href="https://www.dailymail.co.uk/news/article-7667931/Starving-tigers-covered-excrement-tiny-cages-lorry-recovering-Polish-zoo.html"&gt;Starving Tigers Recover in Poznan Zoo&lt;/a&gt; - Daily Mail&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Krakow&lt;/em&gt;  - &lt;a href="https://www.tvn24.pl/tvn24-news-in-english,157,m/inquiry-into-bagatela-theatre-sexual-abuse-scandal-director-on-leave,983828.html"&gt;Bagatela Sexual Harassment&lt;/a&gt;  - TVN (Video)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;TriCity&lt;/em&gt; -  &lt;a href="https://www.maritime-executive.com/article/port-of-gdansk-outlines-3-billion-expansion-plan"&gt;$3 Billion Dollar Port Expansion&lt;/a&gt; - Maritime Executive&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Wroclaw&lt;/em&gt; -  &lt;a href="http://wroclawuncut.com/2019/11/04/strip-club-death-easter-turkish-wroclaw/"&gt;Strip Club Death&lt;/a&gt; - WroclawUncut&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;International&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=asGHu2NzvbI"&gt;Islamophobia in Poland&lt;/a&gt; - Al Jazeera (Video)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://bigdoor24.pl/"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Did you know ?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://bigdoor24.pl/"&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;BigDoor24.pl sends you a zl. 250 retail voucher of your choice for every successful Polish Mortgage Applicant referred - (in addition to what we send them) - register now for your personal referral code.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Sport&lt;/strong&gt; - &lt;a href="https://www.polskieradio.pl/395/7991/Artykul/2399469,Polish-sports-minister-confirmed-as-new-chief-of-WADA"&gt;Pole Heads WADA&lt;/a&gt; - TheNews&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Odds &amp;amp; Ends&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.thefirstnews.com/article/poznan-teen-crowned-transition-queen-after-racking-up-over-85-million-worldwide-followers-on-tik-tok-app-8503"&gt;Poznan Teen named Global Transition Queen on TikTok&lt;/a&gt; - FirstNews&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Podcast&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.bbc.co.uk/programmes/m000678w"&gt;Versailles Treaty History&lt;/a&gt; - BBC&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Have a great Sunday&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Team BigDoor24&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;About BigDoor24.pl&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://bigdoor24.pl/"&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Bigdoor24.pl is a new free service for Expats, finding Property experts who speak your language, securing commission discounts &amp;amp; paying you CashBack on successful Polish mortgage applications. We pay zl. 250 for successful applicant referrals as well as paying the applicant a CashBack. Register for details.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
		<summary>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Today the Shops are CLOSED&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</summary>
	</entry>
	<entry>
		<id>https://bigdoor24.pl/BigDoorWyamBlog/posts/2019-11-05-are-polish-property-agents-a-waste-of-money.html</id>
		<title>Are Polish Property Agents a Waste of Money? - Buying</title>
		<author>
			<name>Team BigDoor24</name>
		</author>
		<link href="https://bigdoor24.pl/BigDoorWyamBlog/posts/2019-11-05-are-polish-property-agents-a-waste-of-money.html" />
		<link rel="enclosure" type="image" href="https://bigdoor24.pl/assets/Images/property-agents-buying.jpg" />
		<updated>2019-11-05T11:35:25Z</updated>
		<content>&lt;p&gt;Following from our initial article in the series, &lt;a href="https://bigdoor24.pl/blog/posts/2019-10-17-are-property-agents-a-waste-of-money.html"&gt;Are Polish Property Agents a Waste of Money/ Selling&lt;/a&gt; we now look at Buying.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In a recent Bloomberg article claiming that &lt;a href="https://www.bloomberg.com/opinion/articles/2019-10-11/real-estate-agents-don-t-deserve-6"&gt;German and American property agents were ripping off their clients&lt;/a&gt; in high fees and low service we decided it was time to look at what Polish property Agents do, don't do and where does your commission go.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To begin, fees in Poland are different from other countries and a basic rule of thumb is that buying or selling will cost you 3 % + VAT of the sale/purchase price whilst renting or letting will cost a months rent + VAT. These are headline costs and as we will explain, there is lots of room for negotiation. Additionally, being aware of these fees can be very important when deciding to sell or let as your buyer or renter will certainly include this information in their decision making.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We would add another feature of the process is that any agent you contract to help can do a deal on your behalf with another agency agent and in most cases they just split the total commission when a deal is completed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the second of our series we will look at&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Buying your Property&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are essentially two types of properties. New developments and second hand properties.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Straight off the bat we would suggest that you should NOT pay commission on buying a new Development. Developers sell the apartments themselves and also use agents, whom they pay a commission to. Agents know that buyers can go directly to a Developer so they do not normally charge a commission. It is for this reason that you should definitely use an agent. You get all the benefit of their wisdom and expertise, along with legal potholes without any extra charge.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For second hand properties, things get a bit more complicated. There is paperwork from the courts, valuation reports, building reports (a broken chimney is not always obvious etc.). If you are well connected you may be able to get your lawyer to do the paperwork but on an hourly rate this can sometimes add up. We would suggest that you definitely get either a lawyer or a property agent to help you but agree a fixed fee beforehand.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;How can a Polish property agent help you ?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When buying any property it is certainly worth having someone who knows the process to help. Agents in Poland are allowed to represent and collect fees from both buyers and sellers of a property. This, we would suggest can easily lead to conflict of interest.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A good agent can ensure that you find the property you want, or at least a good selection based on your requirements. They will arrange property visits, negotiate the price, check the ownership in the courts on the day of signing any agreement, arrange the notary and translator and any valuers/ engineers you need to feel comfortable moving forward. If they are representing both sides then be aware that an agent is primarily trying to get the deal closed at the highest price, in that order.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One way of ensuring that you are not paying too much is to get an official valuation done. Even if you are not getting a Polish mortgage it may still be worthwhile. For added security, consider a small mortgage. This ensures the bank will check all of the elements of the purchase too. If the bank wont lend you money because of the price of the property then maybe you should consider walking away too.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Is this worth 3 % of a purchase price?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Assuming you are buying for zl. 500,000 commission will be zl. 15,000 + VAT  (zl. 18,450 gross) (Less if you go through BigDoor24.pl). That's a lot and if you add in the fact that the seller may also be paying the same amount then that's almost 7.5 % in total of the available budget going to property agents.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The answer really lies in your level of confidence in buying your own property, your access to the property professionals ( lawyers, notaries, valuers etc.) and good access to information on pricing and negotiating skills.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Can you negotiate?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Absolutely.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Property brokers know generally how long the process of buying each type of property is going to take. If it's a second hand apartment that is relatively new then the process will be easier than a farmhouse in the countryside beside agricultural land.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But they want the same fee. Assuming you are pretty clear about what it is you want to buy then it is worth having a conversation with the agent at the beginning and once you have outlined your requirements, ask for a fixed fee that reflects the work involved. A good agent will say no if you go to low but a bad one may not and you will end up with nothing so don't try and low-ball too much. One tactic may be to ask them to suggest a fee that they would be comfortable with. You may be surprised how low they may go. Just engage with one agent rather than lots of them and tell them that they are exclusive. This again can help keep the fee lower and result in a successful process.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Help the Seller, help yourself.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Try to find out through your agent why the seller is selling. If time is a factor this may help you in negotiations. Make an effort to get to know the seller a bit as they are more likely to accommodate someone they like rather than a complete stranger. Enquire what the seller wants to do with the fixtures and furniture and ask as many stupid questions as you can think of as there may not be time later for re-negotiation. Polish sellers regularly take the curtain fittings, plugs or mirrors with them when selling unless already agreed to so do not assume anything when negotiating.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And don't forget, by referring a successful Polish Mortgage applicant to us, BigDoor24.pl, you get zl. 250 and they get zl. 200 for every zl. 100,000 they borrow. &lt;a href="https://bigdoor24.pl/"&gt;Register&lt;/a&gt; for more details and &lt;a href="https://www.facebook.com/bigdoor24/"&gt;Like us now on Facebook&lt;/a&gt; for regular articles on working and living in Poland.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The value of a property agent can be quite a subjective decision but hopefully the above will help you get the most from whatever decision you make. We have lots more articles in our &lt;a href="https://bigdoor24.pl/blog/"&gt;Blog section&lt;/a&gt; that may also help in your adventure.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Happy Buying&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Team BIgDoor24&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
		<summary>&lt;p&gt;Following from our initial article in the series, &lt;a href="https://bigdoor24.pl/blog/posts/2019-10-17-are-property-agents-a-waste-of-money.html"&gt;Are Polish Property Agents a Waste of Money/ Selling&lt;/a&gt; we now look at Buying.&lt;/p&gt;</summary>
	</entry>
	<entry>
		<id>https://bigdoor24.pl/BigDoorWyamBlog/posts/2019-10-17-are-property-agents-a-waste-of-money.html</id>
		<title>Are Polish Property Agents a Waste of Money? - Selling</title>
		<author>
			<name>Team BigDoor24</name>
		</author>
		<link href="https://bigdoor24.pl/BigDoorWyamBlog/posts/2019-10-17-are-property-agents-a-waste-of-money.html" />
		<link rel="enclosure" type="image" href="https://bigdoor24.pl/assets/Images/agent-selling-tips.jpg" />
		<updated>2019-10-17T11:55:16Z</updated>
		<content>&lt;p&gt;In a recent Bloomberg article claiming that &lt;a href="https://www.bloomberg.com/opinion/articles/2019-10-11/real-estate-agents-don-t-deserve-6"&gt;German and American property agents were ripping off their clients&lt;/a&gt; in high fees and low service we decided it was time to look at what Polish property Agents do, don't do and where does your commission go.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To begin, fees in Poland are different from other countries and a basic rule of thumb is that buying or selling will cost you 3 % + VAT of the sale/purchase price whilst renting or letting will cost a months rent + VAT. These are headline costs and as we will explain, there is lots of room for negotiation. Additionally, being aware of these fees can be very important when deciding to sell or let as your buyer or renter will certainly include this information in their decision making.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We would add another feature of the process is that any agent you contract to help can do a deal on your behalf with another agency agent and in most cases they just split the total commission when a deal is completed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the first of our series we will look at&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Selling your Property&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Polish Agents will always ask for an exclusive contract for a defined period of time and indeed some will only accept these types of contracts. In the past, many agents may have been assigned to sell the same property. Agents felt they were actually doing their job by  getting such contracts but the net effect is that a seller has lots of agencies but no real seller. Once the property has been added to the different property portals with nice pictures and fancy text it is , in many cases, forgotten about. Not so with an exclusive offer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So our first piece of advice is give one agent an exclusive contract. Make someone responsible.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Having assigned an agent lets now see what they should do for you.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Time is Money&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you have decided to sell your property then we assume that you would like to sell it immediately. The speed at which you sell it will be determined to a large extent by the price you list at. Advertise to sell at zl. 1 and it is likely you will have a contract by the end of the day. Overvalue the property and your property will soon become stale and give the impression that nobody is interested and there may be something wrong with the property.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The agent should be able to give you a proper guide as to exactly how much you should expect to sell for, how much to advertise it for and this in itself may save you money in either a higher price and/or a quicker sale. When choosing an agent, ask them about other similar properties they have sold in your area to gauge their level of expertise.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once agreed, the agent will check the court records to confirm your ownership and exact measurements as it is their responsibility to ensure that what is being offered is a proper and correct description.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some agents will take pictures only but others may organise video, 3D rendering and compose and publish the adverts on all major property portals. They may also push the property internally to clients of the agency who are looking to buy. Agents pay for the advertising themselves. They may also provide a &amp;quot;For Sale&amp;quot; Banner for display.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once they receive some interest they will arrange viewings and attempt to open up negotiations for a sale. Bad agents just let buyers walk away without finding out why, good agents will always know.  The proper management of this process is crucial as the more feedback you get the better you should be able to tailor your offer and manage the final negotiations. For example, if everyone mentions the noisy dog next door, expect this to be brought up in any final negotiations on price.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Upon completion of the negotiations, the agent will arrange the Notary appointment for both the preliminary and final agreement signings. The buyer may or may not be a direct client of the agent and in a lot of cases may be from a different agency.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once the agreement is signed the agent should then manage the hand over of keys , checking utility levels etc..&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By hiring an agent you also provide some level of trust in the buyer as it would be assumed that they have a legal obligation to ensure the property is transferred properly etc. This may add an un-quantifiable amount to the eventual sale price.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Is this worth 3 % of a sale price?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Assuming you are selling for zl. 500,000 that is zl. 15,000 + VAT  ( zl. 18,450 gross). That's a lot and if you add in the fact that the buyer may also be paying the same amount then that's almost 7.5 % in total of the available budget going to property agents.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The answer really lies in your level of confidence in selling your own property, your access to the advertising portals, ability to correctly value your own property in a constantly moving market and the legal requirements and paperwork&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Can you negotiate?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Absolutely.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To increase your sales price and the number of possible buyers try to demand that the agent does not charge a buyer any commission. This is actually easier than you would think to do as the agency market is quite competitive and a good agent will let you do this.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Try to structure the commission to reflect the effort. Let's imagine you are selling a property worth around zl. 500,000. Well it is likely any fool could sell it for zl. 400,000 so why pay commission on that? Every extra zl. 10,000 an agent gets for you is only worth zl. 300 for them so they wont really care if they get zl. 500,000 or zl. 510,000 .. but you will.Try to structure the commission so you get the optimum amount.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Help the buyer, help yourself.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If a buyer needs a Polish Mortgage they will need an official valuation report from their bank. It may be a good idea for you to commission this report yourself. You can show this to any buyer during negotiations if they wont reach your price and even sell the report to them to use in their mortgage application. The cost can be anything from zl. 500 upwards and make sure the valuer you choose is approved by all banks rather than just a few of them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Don't forget&lt;/strong&gt;, by referring a successful Polish Mortgage applicant to us, BigDoor24.pl, you get zl. 250 and they get zl. 200 for every zl. 100,000 they borrow. &lt;a href="https://bigdoor24.pl/"&gt;Register&lt;/a&gt; for more details and &lt;a href="https://www.facebook.com/bigdoor24/"&gt;Like us now on Facebook&lt;/a&gt; for regular articles on working and living in Poland.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The value of a property agent can be quite a subjective decision but hopefully the above will help you get the most from whatever decision you make.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Happy Selling&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Team BigDoor24&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
		<summary>&lt;p&gt;In a recent Bloomberg article claiming that &lt;a href="https://www.bloomberg.com/opinion/articles/2019-10-11/real-estate-agents-don-t-deserve-6"&gt;German and American property agents were ripping off their clients&lt;/a&gt; in high fees and low service we decided it was time to look at what Polish property Agents do, don't do and where does your commission go.&lt;/p&gt;</summary>
	</entry>
	<entry>
		<id>https://bigdoor24.pl/BigDoorWyamBlog/posts/2019-10-13-the-digest-13th-october-2019.html</id>
		<title>The Digest  - 13th October 2019</title>
		<author>
			<name>Team BigDoor24</name>
		</author>
		<link href="https://bigdoor24.pl/BigDoorWyamBlog/posts/2019-10-13-the-digest-13th-october-2019.html" />
		<link rel="enclosure" type="image" href="https://bigdoor24.pl/assets/Images/thedigest13oct.jpg" />
		<updated>2019-10-13T07:13:24Z</updated>
		<content>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Today the Shops are CLOSED&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Nobel Winner/ Warsaw - Heroin Heist/ Rzeszow - Congress590/ Krakow - Scottish Connection/Tri-City - Museum Review/ Wroclaw - Attacking Equality/ Human Trafficking in Poland/ Lewandowski Triple/ Election Fever/ Economist Radio Podcast Polish Elections and more&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.facebook.com/bigdoor24/"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;If you enjoy The Digest please support and Like us on Facebook, posted every Sunday at 10 am and share to your favourite FB groups now.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="sharethis-inline-share-buttons"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;National&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.theguardian.com/books/2019/oct/10/olga-tokarczuk-the-dreadlocked-feminist-winner-the-nobel-needed?CMP=Share_AndroidApp_Zoho_Mail"&gt;Nobel Poland&lt;/a&gt; - Guardian&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Local&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Warsaw&lt;/em&gt; - &lt;a href="https://www.tvn24.pl/tvn24-news-in-english,157,m/polish-customs-intercept-8-5-kilo-of-heroin-at-warsaw-chopin-airport,976416.html"&gt;Heroin Heist &lt;/a&gt;- TVN&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Rzeszow -&lt;/em&gt; &lt;a href="https://www.thefirstnews.com/article/congress-590-kicks-off-in-rzeszow-7974"&gt;Congress590 Kick Off&lt;/a&gt; - FirstNews&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Krakow&lt;/em&gt;  - &lt;a href="http://www.krakowpost.com/21780/2019/09/krakow-and-edinburgh-renew-their-partnership"&gt;The Scottish Connection&lt;/a&gt; - KrakowPost&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;TriCity&lt;/em&gt; -  &lt;a href="https://www.eurekalert.org/pub_releases/2019-10/dg-mot100919.php"&gt;Museum Review&lt;/a&gt; - Eurekalert&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Wroclaw&lt;/em&gt; -  &lt;a href="http://wroclawuncut.com/2019/10/08/man-who-tried-to-attack-equality-march-is-detained-on-terror-charges/"&gt;Equality Attacked&lt;/a&gt; - WroclawUncut&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;International&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.tvn24.pl/tvn24-news-in-english,157,m/filipino-drivers-exploited-by-human-traffickers-report-by-superwizjer-tvn,972621.html"&gt;Human Trafficking in Poland&lt;/a&gt; - TVN (Video)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://bigdoor24.pl/"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Did you know ?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://bigdoor24.pl/"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;BigDoor24.pl sends you a zl. 250 retail voucher of your choice for every successful Polish Mortgage Applicant referred - (in addition to what we send them) - register now for your personal referral code.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Sport&lt;/strong&gt; - &lt;a href="https://www.polskieradio.pl/395/7790/Artykul/2381731,Football-Poland-beat-Latvia-after-Lewandowski-hattrick"&gt;Lewandowski Hat Trick&lt;/a&gt;  - TheNews&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Odds &amp;amp; Ends&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.npr.org/2019/10/12/768537341/as-an-election-nears-in-poland-church-and-state-are-a-popular-combination?t=1570952359023"&gt;Yeah yeah , we know who is going to win ... Election Review&lt;/a&gt; - NPR&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Podcast&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.economist.com/podcasts/2019/10/11/questions-of-judicial-independence-and-rule-of-law-are-pretty-abstract-to-most-polands-crucial-election"&gt;A Crucial Election&lt;/a&gt; - TheEconomist Podcast&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Have a great Sunday&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Team BigDoor24&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;About BigDoor24.pl&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://bigdoor24.pl/"&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Bigdoor24.pl is a new free service for Expats, finding Property experts who speak your language, securing commission discounts &amp;amp; paying you CashBack on successful Polish mortgage applications. We pay zl. 250 for successful applicant referrals as well as paying the applicant a CashBack. Register for details.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
		<summary>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Today the Shops are CLOSED&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</summary>
	</entry>
	<entry>
		<id>https://bigdoor24.pl/BigDoorWyamBlog/posts/2019-10-06-the-digest-6th-october-2019.html</id>
		<title>The Digest  - 6th October 2019</title>
		<author>
			<name>Team BigDoor24</name>
		</author>
		<link href="https://bigdoor24.pl/BigDoorWyamBlog/posts/2019-10-06-the-digest-6th-october-2019.html" />
		<link rel="enclosure" type="image" href="https://bigdoor24.pl/assets/Images/digest-october-6th.jpg" />
		<updated>2019-10-06T06:59:56Z</updated>
		<content>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Today the Shops are CLOSED&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Swiss Time/ Warsaw - Visa Free/ Katowice - Mine Injuries/Krakow - Killer Air/Tri-City - MotorCross/ Wroclaw - Nazi Trains/ Faith in Poland/ Volley Ball Loss/ Clever Car/ Tesco Fishing and more&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.facebook.com/bigdoor24/"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;If you enjoy The Digest please support and Like us on Facebook, posted every Sunday at 10 am and share to your favourite FB groups now.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="sharethis-inline-share-buttons"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;National&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.bbc.com/news/world-europe-49918910"&gt;Time's Up for Swiss Franc Polish Mortgages&lt;/a&gt; - BBC&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Local&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Warsaw&lt;/em&gt; - &lt;a href="https://www.tvn24.pl/tvn24-news-in-english,157,m/daniel-fried-former-u-s-ambassador-talks-on-visa-waiver-for-poland,974868.html"&gt;Poles to join U.S. Waiver Programme&lt;/a&gt; - TVN (Video)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Katowice&lt;/em&gt; - &lt;a href="https://www.euronews.com/2019/10/03/earthquake-injures-17-inside-polish-coal-mine"&gt;Mine Injuries&lt;/a&gt; - EuroNews&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Krakow&lt;/em&gt;  - &lt;a href="https://www.tvn24.pl/tvn24-news-in-english,157,m/poland-microplastics-discovered-in-the-air-in-krakow,974287.html"&gt;Micro-plastics in the Air&lt;/a&gt; - TVN (Video)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;TriCity&lt;/em&gt; -  &lt;a href="http://www.automobilsport.com/race-categories--24,198548,Gdansk-is-ready-for-action-as-Europes-best-riders-gather-for-Motocross-of-European-Nations,news.htm"&gt;Euro MotorCross &lt;/a&gt;- AutoMobileSport&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Wroclaw&lt;/em&gt; -  &lt;a href="http://wroclawuncut.com/2019/10/01/swastikas-hang-at-dworzec-glowny-for-filming-of-historical-movie/"&gt;Nazi Trains&lt;/a&gt; - WroclawUncut&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;International&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.theguardian.com/world/2019/oct/05/family-faith-flag-catholic-religious-right-battle-polands-soul?CMP=Share_AndroidApp_Zoho_Mail"&gt;Faith in Poland&lt;/a&gt; - The Guardian&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://bigdoor24.pl/"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Did you know ?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://bigdoor24.pl/"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;BigDoor24.pl sends you a zl. 250 retail voucher of your choice for every successful Polish Mortgage Applicant referred - (in addition to what we send them) - register now for your personal referral code.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Sport&lt;/strong&gt; -  &lt;a href="https://www.polskieradio.pl/395/7790/Artykul/2377927,Poland-beaten-by-America-in-Volleyball-World-Cup"&gt;VolleyBall Loss&lt;/a&gt; - TheNews&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Odds &amp;amp; Ends&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.gloucestershirelive.co.uk/news/uk-world-news/stag-party-loses-passport-trip-3393462"&gt;Lost your Passport? Buy a Car &lt;/a&gt;- Gloucestershire Live&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Podcast&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.krakcast.pl/e/krakcast-%e2%80%93-news-1569938770/"&gt;Fishing in Tescos's&lt;/a&gt; - KrakCast&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Have a great Sunday&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Team BigDoor24&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;About BigDoor24.pl&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://bigdoor24.pl/"&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Bigdoor24.pl is a new free service for Expats, finding Property experts who speak your language, securing commission discounts &amp;amp; paying you CashBack on successful Polish mortgage applications. We pay zl. 250 for successful applicant referrals as well as paying the applicant a CashBack. Register for details.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;****&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
		<summary>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Today the Shops are CLOSED&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</summary>
	</entry>
	<entry>
		<id>https://bigdoor24.pl/BigDoorWyamBlog/posts/2019-09-29-the-digest-29th-september-2019.html</id>
		<title>The Digest - 29th September 2019</title>
		<author>
			<name>Team BigDoor24</name>
		</author>
		<link href="https://bigdoor24.pl/BigDoorWyamBlog/posts/2019-09-29-the-digest-29th-september-2019.html" />
		<link rel="enclosure" type="image" href="https://bigdoor24.pl/assets/Images/digest-29sept.jpg" />
		<updated>2019-09-29T07:04:39Z</updated>
		<content>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Today the Shops are OPEN&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;French Attack/ Warsaw - Google Cloud/ Poznan - Bee Good/ More than Buildings/Tri-City - FilmFest/ Wroclaw - U.S. Military/ Stranded Poles/ Volley Ball Jet Rescue/ F35's/ Hampering Hamsters and more&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.facebook.com/bigdoor24/"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;If you enjoy The Digest please support and Like us on Facebook, posted every Sunday at 10 am and share to your favourite FB groups now.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="sharethis-inline-share-buttons"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;National&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.apnews.com/851a13bb93694c44aca3b59797de3a0a"&gt;French Pres. Macron urges Polish Climate Protest&lt;/a&gt; - AP&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Local&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Warsaw&lt;/em&gt; - &lt;a href="https://techcrunch.com/2019/09/27/google-will-soon-open-a-cloud-region-in-poland/?guccounter=1&amp;amp;guce_referrer_us=aHR0cHM6Ly9uZXdzLmdvb2dsZS5jb20v&amp;amp;guce_referrer_cs=g2MLhVG1wAg6KzVe2rHJ3A"&gt;The Google Cloud&lt;/a&gt; - TechCrunch&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Poznan&lt;/em&gt; -  &lt;a href="https://wbj.pl/poznan-promotes-itself-as-a-bee-friendly-city/post/124604"&gt;Bee Friendly City&lt;/a&gt; - WBJ&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Krakow&lt;/em&gt;  -  &lt;a href="https://www.stuff.co.nz/travel/destinations/europe/116037427/krakow-why-theres-more-to-polands-historic-heart-than-just-old-buildings"&gt;Looking past the buildings&lt;/a&gt; - Stuff&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;TriCity&lt;/em&gt; -  &lt;a href="https://tricitynews.pl/the-awards-of-the-44th-polish-film-festival-in-gdynia-photos/"&gt;Movie Awards&lt;/a&gt; - TriCityNews Video&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Wroclaw&lt;/em&gt; -  &lt;a href="http://wroclawuncut.com/2019/09/25/us-military-to-be-based-in-wroclaw-airport/"&gt;U.S. Military Base&lt;/a&gt; - WroclawUncut&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;International&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.tvn24.pl/tvn24-news-in-english,157,m/poland-activates-insurer-s-guarantee-for-neckermann-stranded-tourists,972690.html"&gt;Stranded Poles&lt;/a&gt;  - TVN (Video)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://bigdoor24.pl/"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Did you know ?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://bigdoor24.pl/"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;BigDoor24.pl sends you a zl. 250 retail voucher of your choice for every successful Polish Mortgage Applicant referred - (in addition to what we send them) - register now for your personal referral code.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Sport&lt;/strong&gt; -  &lt;a href="https://www.polskieradio.pl/395/7790/Artykul/2372473,Polish-PM-sends-plane-for-volleyball-team-stuck-in-Amsterdam"&gt;Govt. Jets in to help Volleyball Team&lt;/a&gt; - TheNews&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Odds &amp;amp; Ends&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.polskieradio.pl/395/7785/Artykul/2373967,US-Congress-OKs-sale-of-32-F35-jets-to-Poland-defence-minister"&gt;F35's for Poland approved&lt;/a&gt; - Polskieradio&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Podcast&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.krakcast.pl/e/krakcast-%e2%80%93-news-1569342752/"&gt;Hampering Hamsters&lt;/a&gt; - KrakCast&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Have a great Sunday&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Team BigDoor24&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://bigdoor24.pl/"&gt;About BigDoor24.pl
&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://bigdoor24.pl/"&gt;
Bigdoor24.pl is a new free service for Expats, finding Property experts who speak your language, securing commission discounts &amp;amp; paying you CashBack on successful Polish mortgage applications. We pay zl. 250 for successful applicant referrals as well as paying the applicant a CashBack. Register for details.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
		<summary>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Today the Shops are OPEN&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</summary>
	</entry>
	<entry>
		<id>https://bigdoor24.pl/BigDoorWyamBlog/posts/2019-09-22-rugby-world-cup-2019-best-pubs-to-catch-the-action.html</id>
		<title>Rugby World Cup 2019 - Best Pubs to Catch the Action</title>
		<author>
			<name>Team BigDoor24</name>
		</author>
		<link href="https://bigdoor24.pl/BigDoorWyamBlog/posts/2019-09-22-rugby-world-cup-2019-best-pubs-to-catch-the-action.html" />
		<link rel="enclosure" type="image" href="https://bigdoor24.pl/assets/Images/rugby.jpg" />
		<updated>2019-09-22T07:35:11Z</updated>
		<content>&lt;p&gt;At BigDoor24 we are all about property, much like Rugby ....gaining ground or losing it we can see the parallels.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As the Rugby World Cup begins in Tokyo this week we thought we would list some possible places to watch the (very) early morning games. We understand that it is not available on terrestrial Polish T.V. so these spots may be your best bet for both the game and some atmosphere.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Krakow&lt;/strong&gt; - &lt;a href="https://www.facebook.com/DUFFYSIRISHBAR/"&gt;Duffys Irish Bar&lt;/a&gt; - As one of the best Irish Pubs in the country they are open for all the games.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Gdansk&lt;/strong&gt; - &lt;a href="https://www.facebook.com/pg/Irish-Pub-Piwnica-500146810031489/posts/?ref=page_internal"&gt;Pub Piwnica&lt;/a&gt; - Not showing the earliest of games (Ireland v Scotland 9.45 a.m. today for example) but worth checking out their timetable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Poznan&lt;/strong&gt; - &lt;a href="https://www.facebook.com/tannersirishpub/"&gt;Tanners Irish Pub&lt;/a&gt; - They are opening at 9 a.m. so you may not get the early early games but still plenty to see and enjoy with your fellow fans.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Warsaw&lt;/strong&gt; - We are going to go with &lt;a href="https://www.champions.pl/"&gt;Champions&lt;/a&gt; here as all Irish or British Pubs we checked didn't even seem to know that the rugby was on! .. Happy to be corrected and make changes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Lodz&lt;/strong&gt; - You could try &lt;a href="https://www.facebook.com/FootballPubLodz/?rf=201997076485688"&gt;The Football Pub&lt;/a&gt; but they don't mention if they are open early for the games.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Wroclaw&lt;/strong&gt; - Look in at  &lt;a href="http://thewinnerspub.pl/"&gt;Winners&lt;/a&gt; which opens at 12.00 p.m. so at least you can catch the last games of the day.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Katowice&lt;/strong&gt; - Monopol Hotel has been mentioned as a possible venue but nothing confirmed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our research made pretty clear that there is not a lot of places making any serious effort to show the games. If you know for a fact there is a rugby friendly bar out there please let us know and we will add it to the list.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Have a Great 'Rucking Tournament&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Team BigDoor24&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://bigdoor24.pl"&gt;About BigDoor24.pl
&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://bigdoor24.pl"&gt;
Bigdoor24.pl is a new free service for Expats, finding Property experts who speak your language, securing commission discounts &amp;amp; paying you CashBack on successful Polish mortgage applications. We pay zl. 250 for successful applicant referrals as well as paying the applicant a CashBack. Register for details.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
		<summary>&lt;p&gt;At BigDoor24 we are all about property, much like Rugby ....gaining ground or losing it we can see the parallels.&lt;/p&gt;</summary>
	</entry>
	<entry>
		<id>https://bigdoor24.pl/BigDoorWyamBlog/posts/2019-09-22-the-digest-22-september-2019.html</id>
		<title>The Digest - 22 September 2019</title>
		<author>
			<name>Team BigDoor24</name>
		</author>
		<link href="https://bigdoor24.pl/BigDoorWyamBlog/posts/2019-09-22-the-digest-22-september-2019.html" />
		<link rel="enclosure" type="image" href="https://bigdoor24.pl/assets/Images/digest22sep.jpg" />
		<updated>2019-09-22T06:57:17Z</updated>
		<content>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Today the Shops are CLOSED&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Socialism Up/ Warsaw - Financial Rating/ Poznan - Taxi Driver Superstar/ Krakow - SmogStep/Tri-City - FilmFest/ Wroclaw - Brexit Briefing/ Invading Questions - Russia vs Poland/ Ergo Run/ Film Fest Fracas/ Opening days of WW2 Podcast (again) and more&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.facebook.com/bigdoor24/"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;If you enjoy The Digest please support and Like us on Facebook, posted every Sunday at 10 am and share to your favourite FB groups now.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="sharethis-inline-share-buttons"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;National&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.independent.co.uk/news/world/europe/poland-parliament-polish-socialists-election-left-alliance-spring-razem-a9113881.html"&gt;Socialism on the Rise&lt;/a&gt; - Independent&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Local&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Warsaw&lt;/em&gt; - &lt;a href="https://wbj.pl/warsaw-ranked-64-among-global-financial-centers/post/124595"&gt;Warsaw's Financial Centre Rating&lt;/a&gt; - WBJ&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Poznan&lt;/em&gt; - &lt;a href="https://www.themayor.eu/en/poznan-rewards-taxi-driver-of-the-year"&gt;Taxi Driver of the Year&lt;/a&gt; - TheMayorEU&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Krakow&lt;/em&gt;  -   &lt;a href="https://www.citylab.com/environment/2019/09/krakow-poland-pollution-air-quality-coal-wood-burning-law/597352/"&gt;Another Smog Step&lt;/a&gt; - CityLab&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;TriCity&lt;/em&gt; -  &lt;a href="https://tricitynews.pl/model-united-nations-in-gdansk-2019/"&gt;.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a href="https://tricitynews.pl/the-44th-polish-film-festival-day-1/"&gt;Da FilmFest begins&lt;/a&gt; - TriCityNews Video&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Wroclaw&lt;/em&gt; -  &lt;a href="http://wroclawuncut.com/2019/09/20/british-embassy-to-host-pre-brexit-meeting-in-wroclaw/"&gt;Brexit Briefing&lt;/a&gt;- WroclawUncut&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;International&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.businessinsider.com/russia-poland-subtweeting-each-other-over-invasion-of-poland-2019-9?IR=T"&gt;Who Invaded First - Russia or Poland?&lt;/a&gt;  - Business Insider&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://bigdoor24.pl/"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Did you know ?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://bigdoor24.pl/"&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;BigDoor24.pl sends you a zl. 250 retail voucher of your choice for every successful Polish Mortgage Applicant referred - (in addition to what we send them) - register now for your personal referral code.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Sport&lt;/strong&gt; -  &lt;a href="https://tricitynews.pl/event/the-color-run-at-ergo-arena/"&gt;Ergo Ru&lt;/a&gt;n - TriCity News&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Odds &amp;amp; Ends&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.apnews.com/9759ccf221f446ae819f41e7ed78cc66"&gt;Film Festival Fracas&lt;/a&gt; - AP News&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Podcast&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://play.acast.com/s/dansnowshistoryhit/70edd6ca-66c0-45b4-8aef-76c96b6c52c0"&gt;First days of WW2 Invasion of Poland&lt;/a&gt; - BBC (That good we included it again today for those who missed it)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Have a great Autumnal Sunday&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Team BigDoor24&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
		<summary>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Today the Shops are CLOSED&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</summary>
	</entry>
	<entry>
		<id>https://bigdoor24.pl/BigDoorWyamBlog/posts/2019-09-18-why-is-it-easier-to-get-work-permit-in-some-areas-and-not-in-others.html</id>
		<title>Work Permit - Why are some Polish provinces easier than others?</title>
		<author>
			<name>Team BigDoor24</name>
		</author>
		<link href="https://bigdoor24.pl/BigDoorWyamBlog/posts/2019-09-18-why-is-it-easier-to-get-work-permit-in-some-areas-and-not-in-others.html" />
		<link rel="enclosure" type="image" href="https://bigdoor24.pl/assets/Images/work-permit-queue.jpg" />
		<updated>2019-09-18T09:06:14Z</updated>
		<content>&lt;p&gt;Anyone who has tried to obtain a work permit in Poland these days knows the wait time can be extraordinarily long, hampering both the efforts of the prospective worker and the employer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;According to a recent &lt;a href="https://www.money.pl/gospodarka/ukraincy-w-polsce-w-urzedach-zniechecaja-sie-do-pracy-ale-posrednicy-znalezli-sposob-6425422569510529a.html"&gt;money.pl article&lt;/a&gt;, there is a great disparity in the time taken to obtain a work permit from the different Vovoidships (Provinces) and Polish businesses are adapting.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The article explains how businesses and intermediaries are targeting those provinces that are responding quicker to applications by setting up registered businesses in each area and when they locate a more efficient service, moving all of their applications there.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While the law is concerned about the location of the business making the application , they are not concerned about where in Poland the actual work is carried out. Combined with on the ground research (calling the local government agencies and enquiring about application backlogs etc. ) these businesses move applications to their conclusion as quickly as possible. This will not solve all of the delay issues and recent legislation changes do not seem to have been effective.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://bigdoor24.pl/"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Did you know?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://bigdoor24.pl/"&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;BigDoor24.pl sends you a zl. 250 retail voucher of your choice for every successful Polish Mortgage Applicant referred - (in addition to what we send them) - register now for your personal referral code.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The average wait time is supposed to be 30 days but is now closer to 90 with many application refusals being contested through the court system. An average department worker receives 1,900 per month and staffing levels are low and getting lower.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The net effect is that over 75 % of Ukrainians cite the delays and complexities of the application process to be a major contributory factor to leaving Poland and working elsewhere.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So next time you or a friend needs to apply for a work permit, make sure to enquire how the intermediary plans to get you one. It may make a big difference.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Team BigDoor24.pl&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://bigdoor24.pl/"&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;About BigDoor24.pl&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://bigdoor24.pl/"&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Bigdoor24.pl is a new free service for Expats, finding Property experts who speak your language, securing commission discounts &amp;amp; paying you CashBack on successful Polish mortgage applications.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
		<summary>&lt;p&gt;Anyone who has tried to obtain a work permit in Poland these days knows the wait time can be extraordinarily long, hampering both the efforts of the prospective worker and the employer.&lt;/p&gt;</summary>
	</entry>
	<entry>
		<id>https://bigdoor24.pl/BigDoorWyamBlog/posts/2019-09-14-the-digest-14th-september-2019.html</id>
		<title>The Digest  - 15th September 2019</title>
		<author>
			<name>Team BigDoor24</name>
		</author>
		<link href="https://bigdoor24.pl/BigDoorWyamBlog/posts/2019-09-14-the-digest-14th-september-2019.html" />
		<link rel="enclosure" type="image" href="https://bigdoor24.pl/assets/Images/digest-15sept.jpg" />
		<updated>2019-09-14T19:32:56Z</updated>
		<content>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Today the Shops are CLOSED&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Greenpeace in Gdansk/  Warsaw - Minimum Wage Increase/ Krakow - Date Rape Drug Detection/Tri-City - Model U.N./ Wroclaw - E Scooter Tragedy/ Polish Planet/ Apex in Krakow/ Anne Frank in US/ Opening days of WW2 Podcast and more&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.facebook.com/bigdoor24/"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;If you enjoy The Digest please support and Like us on Facebook, posted every Sunday at 10 am and share to your favourite FB groups now.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="sharethis-inline-share-buttons"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;National&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://en.rfi.fr/contenu/20190910-polish-guards-board-greenpeaces-rainbow-warrior-coal-clash"&gt;Border Guards board Greenpeace ship&lt;/a&gt; - rFI&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Local&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Warsaw&lt;/em&gt; - &lt;a href="https://www.tvn24.pl/tvn24-news-in-english,157,m/poland-s-kaczynski-says-minimum-wage-increase-safe-for-small-businesses,968821.html"&gt;Minimum wage rise wont affect SME sector, apparently&lt;/a&gt; - TVN Video&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Krakow&lt;/em&gt;  -  &lt;a href="http://www.krakowpost.com/21716/2019/08/date-rape-drug-bracelet"&gt;Date Rape Drug Detection&lt;/a&gt; - KrakowPost&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;TriCity&lt;/em&gt; -  &lt;a href="https://tricitynews.pl/model-united-nations-in-gdansk-2019/"&gt;Model U.N.&lt;/a&gt; - TriCityNews&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Wroclaw&lt;/em&gt; -  &lt;a href="http://wroclawuncut.com/2019/09/13/tragedy-as-25-year-old-dies-in-e-scooter-accident/"&gt;E-Scootet Tragedy&lt;/a&gt; - WroclawUncut&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;International&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://poland.pl/science/achievements-science/ciri-wolin-or-boruta-are-the-proposed-names-for-the-polish-planet/"&gt;Naming the Polish Planet&lt;/a&gt;  - Poland.pl&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://bigdoor24.pl/"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Did you know ?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://bigdoor24.pl/"&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;BigDoor24.pl sends you a zl. 250 retail voucher of your choice for every successful Polish Mortgage Applicant referred - (in addition to what we send them) - register now for your personal referral code.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Sport&lt;/strong&gt; -  &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=TiZtGZ3yJgM"&gt;Apex Legends competition to begin in Krakow&lt;/a&gt; - APEX ( YouTube)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Odds &amp;amp; Ends&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.polskieradio.pl/395/7791/Artykul/2368110,Diary-of-%E2%80%98Polish-Anne-Frank%E2%80%99-to-be-released-in-US"&gt;Polish Anne Frank&lt;/a&gt; - TheNews&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Podcast&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://play.acast.com/s/dansnowshistoryhit/70edd6ca-66c0-45b4-8aef-76c96b6c52c0"&gt;First days of WW2 Invasion of Poland&lt;/a&gt; - BBC&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Have a great Sunday&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Team BigDoor24&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
		<summary>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Today the Shops are CLOSED&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</summary>
	</entry>
	<entry>
		<id>https://bigdoor24.pl/BigDoorWyamBlog/posts/2019-09-11-how-will-doubling-the-minimum-wage-affect-polish-property.html</id>
		<title>How will Doubling the Minimum Wage affect Polish Property</title>
		<author>
			<name>Team BigDoor24</name>
		</author>
		<link href="https://bigdoor24.pl/BigDoorWyamBlog/posts/2019-09-11-how-will-doubling-the-minimum-wage-affect-polish-property.html" />
		<link rel="enclosure" type="image" href="https://bigdoor24.pl/assets/Images/double-wage.jpg" />
		<updated>2019-09-11T12:04:41Z</updated>
		<content>&lt;p&gt;The Government announced plans this week to &lt;a href="https://www.bloomberg.com/news/articles/2019-09-09/poland-s-plan-to-skyrocket-minimum-wages-heralds-economic-shift"&gt;double the Polish minimum wage over the next 4 years&lt;/a&gt; (Bloomberg), should they be re-elected. What effect will this have on future Polish property prices?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Arguments about the validity and effect of minimum wages are notoriously under researched and the effect on property even more so. We can't definitively say what the future will bring but we can suggest particular areas to watch out for.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;More cash, more splash&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All things being equal - supply , demand, economic growth and employment levels - any increase in disposable income will automatically lead to an increase in property prices and rents demanded. Added to the fact that Poland already has lower than EU average levels of mortgages, a singular view should see Polish property growth to seriously move up in the next 4 years and beyond.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Inflation&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Any increase in disposable income in the general population normally leads to an increase in inflation. Central banks don't like too much inflation which may lead to an increase in polish mortgage interest rates, dampening peoples ability to spend. Any increase in the cost of borrowing would generally have a negative effect on property. If the low levels of polish mortgages continue this may not have as large an effect as it might.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Over time, property is considered a good hedge (safeguard) against rising inflation so an investor may be happy to ride out any slowdowns.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Employment&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the main arguments made against minimum wages is the effect on employment. The claim is made that by making staff more expensive, employers will hire less and this will also lead to a drop in new businesses opening. The nuance here is that it really depends on what the minimum wage is. There is no doubt that a doubling of the current rate would have a dramatic effect and should it lead to large scale unemployment then a serious drop in property values would be expected.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The BigDoor24 Team view&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is a big gamble and the strength of the economy probably gives them confidence of it's positive effects but assuming it actually happens we would suggest that generally it should be Property Positive. We would add that this approach is an indication of a wider vision, right or wrong, of a future strong Polish economy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We believe increasing polish mortgage levels will have a much more upward effect on rising prices than minimum wages and we don't see any reason for a serious slowdown in the near future.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But hey, don't take our word for it and do your own research, it's a choppy world out there!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Team BigDoor24&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Did you know?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://bigdoor24.pl/"&gt;
BigDoor24.pl sends you a zl. 250 retail voucher of your choice for every successful Polish Mortgage Applicant referred - (in addition to what we send them) - register now for your personal referral code.
&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;About Team BigDoor24.pl&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://bigdoor24.pl/"&gt;
Bigdoor24.pl is a new free service for Expats, finding Property experts who speak your language, securing commission discounts &amp;amp; paying you CashBack on successful Polish mortgage applications.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
		<summary>&lt;p&gt;The Government announced plans this week to &lt;a href="https://www.bloomberg.com/news/articles/2019-09-09/poland-s-plan-to-skyrocket-minimum-wages-heralds-economic-shift"&gt;double the Polish minimum wage over the next 4 years&lt;/a&gt; (Bloomberg), should they be re-elected. What effect will this have on future Polish property prices?&lt;/p&gt;</summary>
	</entry>
	<entry>
		<id>https://bigdoor24.pl/BigDoorWyamBlog/posts/2019-09-09-how-safe-is-your-city.html</id>
		<title>How Safe is your City?</title>
		<author>
			<name>Team BigDoor24.pl</name>
		</author>
		<link href="https://bigdoor24.pl/BigDoorWyamBlog/posts/2019-09-09-how-safe-is-your-city.html" />
		<link rel="enclosure" type="image" href="https://bigdoor24.pl/assets/Images/burglary.jpg" />
		<updated>2019-09-09T15:07:57Z</updated>
		<content>&lt;p&gt;The official numbers are out from the &lt;a href="https://policja.maps.arcgis.com/apps/MapSeries/index.html?appid=b5fc08aaa8a54296b418383584313263"&gt;National Map of Security Risks&lt;/a&gt; detailing amongst others, the number of reported burglaries by Vovoidship for the period January to June 2019.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Keep in mind, when &lt;a href="https://ec.europa.eu/eurostat/statistics-explained/images/d/d9/Burglary_of_private_residential_premises%2C_2016_%28police-recorded_offences_per_100_000_inhabitants%29.png"&gt;compared to other EU countries&lt;/a&gt;, Poland is very much at the very low  end of the scale.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="./assets/Images/burglarychart2.jpg" class="img-fluid img-responsive" alt="" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Common sense should be enough to keep your valuables safe and unless something of particular value is taken, reporting the issue to the Police may add to your headache but of course, whatever makes you feel safer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you do call the Police ( 997), remember to preface it with the city code ( i.e .22 997 for Warsaw)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Additionally, if you are a renter, you should definitely inform your landlord and don't be hesitant to demand better security should you feel it's necessary.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Stay safe,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Team BigDoor24&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://bigdoor24.pl"&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Did you know ?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://bigdoor24.pl"&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;BigDoor24.pl sends you a zl. 250 retail voucher of your choice for every successful Polish Mortgage Applicant referred - (in addition to what we send them) - register now for your personal referral code.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;About Team BigDoor24.pl&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://bigdoor24.pl/"&gt;Bigdoor24.pl is a new free service for Expats, finding Property experts who speak your language, securing commission discounts &amp;amp; paying you CashBack on successful Polish mortgage applications.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
		<summary>&lt;p&gt;The official numbers are out from the &lt;a href="https://policja.maps.arcgis.com/apps/MapSeries/index.html?appid=b5fc08aaa8a54296b418383584313263"&gt;National Map of Security Risks&lt;/a&gt; detailing amongst others, the number of reported burglaries by Vovoidship for the period January to June 2019.&lt;/p&gt;</summary>
	</entry>
	<entry>
		<id>https://bigdoor24.pl/BigDoorWyamBlog/posts/2019-08-25-the-digest-25th-august-2019.html</id>
		<title>The Digest - 25th August 2019</title>
		<author>
			<name>Team BigDoor24</name>
		</author>
		<link href="https://bigdoor24.pl/BigDoorWyamBlog/posts/2019-08-25-the-digest-25th-august-2019.html" />
		<link rel="enclosure" type="image" href="https://bigdoor24.pl/assets/Images/digest-25-august.jpg" />
		<updated>2019-08-25T06:58:48Z</updated>
		<content>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Today the Shops are OPEN&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Tatra Tragedy/  Warsaw - Legia v Rangers/ Krakow - Russian Rumble/Tri-City - Street Racing/ Wroclaw - Residency Permit Problems/ Indian Visit/ Sport - Aussie Rules/Interpol Hunt and more&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.facebook.com/bigdoor24/"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;If you enjoy The Digest please support and Like us on Facebook, posted every Sunday at 10 am and share to your favourite FB groups now.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="sharethis-inline-share-buttons"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;National&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.bbc.com/news/world-europe-49439619"&gt;Killer Lightening in Tatra Mountains&lt;/a&gt; - BBC&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Local&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Warsaw&lt;/em&gt; -  &lt;a href="https://www.theguardian.com/football/2019/aug/22/europa-league-roundup-celtic-aik-rangers-legia-warsaw-linfield-qarabag"&gt;Legia Warsaw vs. Rangers&lt;/a&gt;- Guardian&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Krakow&lt;/em&gt;  -  &lt;a href="https://tass.com/society/1072134"&gt;10 Russians detained&lt;/a&gt; - Tass&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;TriCity&lt;/em&gt; - &lt;a href="https://tricitynews.pl/event/verva-street-racing-2019-in-gdynia/"&gt;Street racing&lt;/a&gt; - TriCityNews&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Wroclaw&lt;/em&gt; -  &lt;a href="http://wroclawuncut.com/2019/08/20/report-confirms-polish-authorities-cant-cope-with-immigration-influx/"&gt;Res. Permit Avalanche&lt;/a&gt; - WroclawUncut&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;International&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://timesofindia.indiatimes.com/india/strengthening-ties-jaishankar-to-travel-to-hungary-russia-and-poland-from-sunday/articleshow/70820707.cms"&gt;First high level visit to Poland in 30 years from Indian Govt.&lt;/a&gt; - Times of India&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://bigdoor24.pl/"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Did you know ?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://bigdoor24.pl/"&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;BigDoor24.pl sends you a zl. 250 retail voucher of your choice for every successful Polish Mortgage Applicant referred - (in addition to what we send them) - register now for your personal referral code.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Sport&lt;/strong&gt; - &lt;a href="https://www.polskieradio.pl/395/7790/Artykul/2356897,Polands-Australian-Footy-team-gears-up-for-unusual-friendly"&gt;Aussie Rules in Poland&lt;/a&gt; - thenews&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Odds &amp;amp; Ends&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.tvn24.pl/tvn24-news-in-english,157,m/magdalena-kralka-polish-suspect-is-wanted-by-interpol,963014.html"&gt;Female Drug Gang Leader hunted by Interpol&lt;/a&gt; - TVN Video&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Podcast&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Krakcast&lt;/em&gt; - &lt;a href="https://www.krakcast.pl/e/krakcast-rant-snacks/"&gt;The Rant&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Have a great Sunday&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Team BigDoor24&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
		<summary>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Today the Shops are OPEN&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</summary>
	</entry>
	<entry>
		<id>https://bigdoor24.pl/BigDoorWyamBlog/posts/2019-08-19-25-of-ukrainians-may-leave-poland-in-2020-national-bank-of-poland-nbp.html</id>
		<title>25% of Ukrainians may leave Poland in 2020 - National Bank of Poland (NBP)</title>
		<author>
			<name>Team BigDoor24</name>
		</author>
		<link href="https://bigdoor24.pl/BigDoorWyamBlog/posts/2019-08-19-25-of-ukrainians-may-leave-poland-in-2020-national-bank-of-poland-nbp.html" />
		<link rel="enclosure" type="image" href="https://bigdoor24.pl/assets/Images/ukrainian-leave.jpg" />
		<updated>2019-08-19T10:51:09Z</updated>
		<content>&lt;p&gt;According to a recent &lt;a href="https://www.money.pl/gielda/nbp-liczba-ukraincow-pracujacych-w-polsce-zmniejszy-sie-o-20-25-w-ciagu-4-lat-6415172090214529a.html"&gt;report&lt;/a&gt; from the NBP's Dept. of Economic Analysis the expected 2020 legislation in Germany, allowing work permits for non-EU citizens, may result in a reduction of the number of Ukrainians working and living in Poland by 20 to 25 % from current levels.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The department, as reported in Money.pl , has said that this is the maximum number expected and may well be less. The profile of the Ukrainian in Poland has become more settled in recent years with many bringing their families to Poland and buying property.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The actual number of those to leave will depend greatly on the terms of the eventual German legislation and the state of the German economy in 2020.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At current levels of approximately 2 million Ukrainians working across the different levels of the Polish economy this would mean up to 400,000 to 500,000 less Ukrainians in the Polish workforce. As the economy has experienced a recent slight slowdown, considered by many to be a welcome adjustment, the NBP does not believe it will have a greatly negative effect on workforce pressures.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://bigdoor24.pl"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Did you know ?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://bigdoor24.pl"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;BigDoor24.pl sends you a zl. 250 retail voucher of your choice for every successful Polish Mortgage Applicant referred - (in addition to what we send them) - register now for your personal referral code.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Effect on Polish Property Market&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We do not believe that this will have a major impact on the Polish property market. Rental levels will remain the same we believe in the next 12 months generally and any shortfall in demand will be compensated for by rising wages.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In terms of buyers, demand is continuing to increase year on year and another &lt;a href="http://www.nbp.pl/home.aspx?f=/aktualnosci/wiadomosci_2019/kredytowy2019_3.html"&gt;recent report from the NBP&lt;/a&gt; says that bank lending in the Polish mortgage market has also increased, if only at a slightly less dynamic level.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Despite this view we would urge our readers to keep an eye on developments over the next 12 months as many of the NBP estimates come with large caveats and the danger of  a global slowdown is being highlighted in international media.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;About Team BigDoor24.pl&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://bigdoor24.pl/"&gt;Bigdoor24.pl is a new free service for Expats, finding Property experts who speak your language, securing commission discounts &amp;amp; paying you CashBack on successful Polish mortgage applications.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
		<summary>&lt;p&gt;According to a recent &lt;a href="https://www.money.pl/gielda/nbp-liczba-ukraincow-pracujacych-w-polsce-zmniejszy-sie-o-20-25-w-ciagu-4-lat-6415172090214529a.html"&gt;report&lt;/a&gt; from the NBP's Dept. of Economic Analysis the expected 2020 legislation in Germany, allowing work permits for non-EU citizens, may result in a reduction of the number of Ukrainians working and living in Poland by 20 to 25 % from current levels.&lt;/p&gt;</summary>
	</entry>
	<entry>
		<id>https://bigdoor24.pl/BigDoorWyamBlog/posts/2019-08-17-the-digest-18th-august-2019.html</id>
		<title>The Digest  - 18th August 2019</title>
		<author>
			<name>Team BigDoor24</name>
		</author>
		<link href="https://bigdoor24.pl/BigDoorWyamBlog/posts/2019-08-17-the-digest-18th-august-2019.html" />
		<link rel="enclosure" type="image" href="https://bigdoor24.pl/assets/Images/digest-18-august.jpg" />
		<updated>2019-08-17T18:09:53Z</updated>
		<content>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Today the Shops are CLOSED&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Blow Reform/  Warsaw - Craft Beer/ Krakow - Steel Fire/ Lodz - Liver Buster/ Tri-City - Teutonic Knights/ Poznan - Malta Modify/ Wroclaw - Bus Lane Bikers/ Rights Commissioner Speaks/ Sport - Team Triumphs/Fluent Foreigners and more&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.facebook.com/bigdoor24/"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;If you enjoy The Digest please support and Like us on Facebook, posted every Sunday at 10 am and share to your favourite FB groups now.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="sharethis-inline-share-buttons"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;National&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://cannabisindustryjournal.com/feature_article/poland-pushes-forward-on-reform/"&gt;Poland's Cannabis Reforms&lt;/a&gt; - Cannabis Industry Journal&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Local&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Warsaw&lt;/em&gt; -  &lt;a href="https://edition.cnn.com/travel/article/best-beer-cities/index.html"&gt;Craft Beer City&lt;/a&gt; - CNN Travel&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Krakow&lt;/em&gt;  -  &lt;a href="https://www.reuters.com/article/us-poland-arcelormittal-sa/fire-at-arcelormittal-steel-plant-in-poland-extinguished-idUSKCN1V5238"&gt;Steel Fire&lt;/a&gt; - Reuters&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Lodz -&lt;/em&gt;  &lt;a href="https://www.thefirstnews.com/article/lodz-firm-produces-fat-busting-drug-which-could-save-450-million-globally-from-liver-disease-6740"&gt;Liver disease busting drug developed&lt;/a&gt; - First News&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;TriCity&lt;/em&gt; - &lt;a href="https://tricitynews.pl/teutonic-knights-invite-for-a-tea-krzyzakon-2019/"&gt;Teutonic Knights&lt;/a&gt;  - TriCityNews&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Poznan&lt;/em&gt; - &lt;a href="https://wbj.pl/poznans-galeria-malta-being-revamped/post/124179"&gt;Galeria Malta Revamp&lt;/a&gt; - WBJ&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Wroclaw&lt;/em&gt; -  &lt;a href="http://wroclawuncut.com/2019/08/14/city-allow-motorcyclists-to-use-bus-lanes/"&gt;Bus Lane Bikers&lt;/a&gt; - WroclawUncut&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;International&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.reuters.com/article/us-poland-rights/polands-rights-commissioner-on-faultlines-of-divided-country-idUSKCN1V316A"&gt;Poland's Rights Commissioner Speaks&lt;/a&gt; - Reuters&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://bigdoor24.pl/"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Did you know ?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://bigdoor24.pl/"&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;BigDoor24.pl sends you a zl. 250 retail voucher of your choice for every successful Polish Mortgage Applicant referred - (in addition to what we send them) - register now for your personal referral code.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Sport&lt;/strong&gt; - &lt;a href="https://www.iaaf.org/news/report/poland-wins-2019-european-team-championships"&gt;Team Title Triumph&lt;/a&gt; - iaaf.org&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Odds &amp;amp; Ends&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.kyivpost.com/ukraine-politics/radio-poland-ukrainian-wins-international-polish-language-competition.html"&gt;Ukrainian Wins Polish Language Competition&lt;/a&gt; - Kyiv Post&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Podcast&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Krakcast&lt;/em&gt; - &lt;a href="https://www.krakcast.pl/e/krakcast-news-1565714165/"&gt;Scooters&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Have a great Sunday&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Team BigDoor24&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
		<summary>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Today the Shops are CLOSED&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</summary>
	</entry>
	<entry>
		<id>https://bigdoor24.pl/BigDoorWyamBlog/posts/2019-08-04-the-digest-4th-august-2019.html</id>
		<title>The Digest - 4th August 2019</title>
		<author>
			<name>Team BigDoor24</name>
		</author>
		<link href="https://bigdoor24.pl/BigDoorWyamBlog/posts/2019-08-04-the-digest-4th-august-2019.html" />
		<link rel="enclosure" type="image" href="https://bigdoor24.pl/assets/Images/digest-4th2019.jpg" />
		<updated>2019-08-04T06:30:24Z</updated>
		<content>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Today the Shops are CLOSED&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Tackling the Banks/  Warsaw - Remembering/ Krakow - Rainbow Plague Piffle/ Lodz - Eco Lead/ Tri-City - Siren Call/ Poznan - New Museum/ Wroclaw - Speedway soon/ Poland shaped by Tyrants/ Sport - Polonia Tour/Flocking Foreigners and more&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.facebook.com/bigdoor24/"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;If you enjoy The Digest please support and Like us on Facebook, posted every Sunday at 10 am and share to your favourite FB groups now.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="sharethis-inline-share-buttons"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;National&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.bloomberg.com/news/articles/2019-08-04/poland-s-32-billion-mortgage-fiasco-gets-its-day-in-eu-court"&gt;Banks tackled in EU court over Polish Swiss Franc Mortgage Fiasco&lt;/a&gt; - Bloomberg&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Local&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Warsaw&lt;/em&gt; -   &lt;a href="https://www.aljazeera.com/indepth/features/warsaw-stops-remember-1944-uprising-190731200449274.html"&gt;Remembering&lt;/a&gt; - Al Jazeera&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Krakow&lt;/em&gt;  -   &lt;a href="https://www.cnsnews.com/blog/michael-w-chapman/arbp-krakow-gay-rainbow-plague-wants-control-our-souls-hearts-and-minds"&gt;Rainbow Plague in 21st Century&lt;/a&gt; - CNS News&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Lodz -&lt;/em&gt;  &lt;a href="https://www.themayor.eu/ga/lodz-assumes-the-leadership-over-the-polish-eco-strategy"&gt;City assumes leadership role in Polish Eco Strategy&lt;/a&gt; - Mayor.eu&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;TriCity&lt;/em&gt; -  &lt;a href="https://tricitynews.pl/why-do-sirens-go-off-every-august-the-1st-in-poland/"&gt;Sirens on the 1st, an explanation&lt;/a&gt; - TriCityNews&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Poznan&lt;/em&gt; - &lt;a href="https://www.thefirstnews.com/article/design-announced-for-new-museum-on-the-greater-poland-uprising-7010"&gt;New Museum Design&lt;/a&gt; - FirstNews&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Wroclaw&lt;/em&gt; - &lt;a href="http://wroclawuncut.com/2019/08/02/__trashed-2/"&gt;Speedway in Wroclaw&lt;/a&gt; - WroclawUncut&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;International&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.wsj.com/articles/how-hitler-and-stalin-made-modern-poland-11564613692"&gt;How Stalin &amp;amp; Hitler made modern Poland&lt;/a&gt; - Wall Street Journal&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://bigdoor24.pl/"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Did you know ?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://bigdoor24.pl/"&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;BigDoor24.pl sends you a zl. 250 retail voucher of your choice for every successful Polish Mortgage Applicant referred - (in addition to what we send them) - register now for your personal referral code.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Sport&lt;/strong&gt; - &lt;a href="https://www.cyclingweekly.com/news/racing/tour-poland-2019-start-list-433577"&gt;Tour Of Polonia&lt;/a&gt; - Cycling Weekly&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Odds &amp;amp; Ends&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://streetwise.pl/2019/08/01/foreigners-in-poland-with-permanent-residence-permits-booming/"&gt;Flocking Foreigners &lt;/a&gt;- StreetWise&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Podcast&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Krakcast&lt;/em&gt; - &lt;a href="https://www.krakcast.pl/"&gt;It's holiday time so they are still playing the hits&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Have a great Sunday&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Team BigDoor24&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
		<summary>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Today the Shops are CLOSED&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</summary>
	</entry>
	<entry>
		<id>https://bigdoor24.pl/BigDoorWyamBlog/posts/2019-07-29-love-the-sun-hate-the-heat-air-condition-tips-in-poland.html</id>
		<title>Love the Sun, Hate the Heat - Air Conditioner Tips in Poland</title>
		<author>
			<name>Team BigDoor24</name>
		</author>
		<link href="https://bigdoor24.pl/BigDoorWyamBlog/posts/2019-07-29-love-the-sun-hate-the-heat-air-condition-tips-in-poland.html" />
		<link rel="enclosure" type="image" href="https://bigdoor24.pl/BigDoorWyamBlog/assets/Images/aircondition.jpg" />
		<updated>2019-07-29T12:50:31Z</updated>
		<content>&lt;p&gt;There are lots of articles out there that detail the different types of Air Conditioning to get this summer. From the small portable units with their varying prices, energy efficiency and bacterial effects to the built-in multi-room wall controlled ones, there is a lot to choose from.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If, however, you are planning to rent in the near future, are currently renting or you are an owner then here are some Polish market-centric things you may want to be aware of.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Wall Mounted Air-Conditioners&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Old Tenement Buildings&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Due to the high ceilings and thick walls they tend to be substantially naturally cooler in the summer. The downside is that in winter, control of the heating may be out of your hands as the central heating is controlled by committee. Additionally, heating costs can also be higher in these buildings.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While it is possible to install new inbuilt wall mounted air conditioners you will need to check with the building committee to see what is allowed, legal and prohibited as some properties may have historical listings that could hamper any installation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;New Apartments&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As an owner you should generally have no problem to install aircon but again, check your community regulations to make sure there is no issue.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As a renter, there is increasing demand for better quality units with air conditioning already in place. If you are currently looking, make sure to mention to the agent that AC is required. There is no guarantee as the property portals don't regularly allow you to search for this particular feature (try in keyword search where possible).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Alternatively, and we have heard that this is not only possible but also quite effective, offer to do a deal with your landlord.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The normal useage period for a new AC is 3 years (and they can offset the costs against tax for the same period) so ask your landlord to buy you one and share the costs on a monthly basis. It would be in the landlords interest to have it in place for the next rental as they should be able to charge a slightly higher rent. At the same time, this saves you shelling out for a better AC without the hassle of moving it if required to a new place.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://bigdoor24.pl/"&gt;
Did you know ?
&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://bigdoor24.pl/"&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://bigdoor24.pl/"&gt;BigDoor24.pl sends you a zl. 250 retail voucher of your choice for every successful Polish Mortgage Applicant referred - (in addition to what we send them) - register now for your personal referral code.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Portable Air Conditioners&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you are happy to just go for a portable that you can move from room to room, or indeed a big electric fan, then there are lots to choose from in Leroy Merlin, Auchan, Media markt etc. Or you could check out allegro.pl for second hand options.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As for the types of Air Conditioners to go for ... that's what google is for :-)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Keep cool!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Team BigDoor24.pl&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://bigdoor24.pl/"&gt;About BigDoor24.pl - BigDoor24.pl is a free service that finds property experts who speak your language, locking in commission discounts and paying you cashbacks on successful Polish Mortgage applications.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
		<summary>&lt;p&gt;There are lots of articles out there that detail the different types of Air Conditioning to get this summer. From the small portable units with their varying prices, energy efficiency and bacterial effects to the built-in multi-room wall controlled ones, there is a lot to choose from.&lt;/p&gt;</summary>
	</entry>
	<entry>
		<id>https://bigdoor24.pl/BigDoorWyamBlog/posts/2019-07-27-the-digest-28th-july-2019.html</id>
		<title>The Digest - 28th July 2019</title>
		<author>
			<name>Team BigDoor24</name>
		</author>
		<link href="https://bigdoor24.pl/BigDoorWyamBlog/posts/2019-07-27-the-digest-28th-july-2019.html" />
		<link rel="enclosure" type="image" href="https://bigdoor24.pl/assets/Images/digest28july.jpg" />
		<updated>2019-07-27T18:32:46Z</updated>
		<content>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Today the Shops are OPEN&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Zl. 2.8 Billion Ball Rolling/  Warsaw - People's Rights Wronged/ Krakow - Hero Time Again/ Lodz - Hotel Homage/ Tri-City - Bungee Bungle/ Wroclaw - Tossers Attack/ Poland Vs. EU (again)/ Sport - Polonia Games/ Electric Solutions and more&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.facebook.com/bigdoor24/"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;If you enjoy The Digest please support and Like us on Facebook, posted every Sunday at 10 am and share to your favourite FB groups now.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="sharethis-inline-share-buttons"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;National&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.bloomberg.com/news/articles/2019-07-24/poland-lures-private-equity-with-737-million-co-investment-plan"&gt;Govt. commits Zl. 2.8 billion to lure private investors&lt;/a&gt; - Bloomberg&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Local&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Warsaw&lt;/em&gt; -  &lt;a href="https://www.theguardian.com/world/2019/jul/27/poland-march-warsaw-support-lgbt-rights-pride-violence"&gt;People marching for people rights&lt;/a&gt; - The Guardian&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Krakow&lt;/em&gt;  -  &lt;a href="https://time.com/5635746/the-remarkable-story-of-the-man-who-volunteered-to-enter-auschwitz-and-tell-the-world-about-it/"&gt;Yet another Hero story&lt;/a&gt; - Time Magazine&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Lodz -&lt;/em&gt; &lt;a href="https://www.psfk.com/2019/07/puro-lodz-hotel-cinema-history.html"&gt;Hotels Homage to History&lt;/a&gt; - PSFK&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;TriCity&lt;/em&gt; -   &lt;a href="https://tricitynews.pl/bungee-accident-in-gdynia/"&gt;Bungee Accident&lt;/a&gt; - TriCityNews&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Wroclaw&lt;/em&gt; - &lt;a href="http://wroclawuncut.com/2019/07/26/wroclawian-attacked-for-publicly-criticising-homophobic-graffiti/"&gt;Saps attack&lt;/a&gt; - WroclawUncut&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;International&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.pbs.org/newshour/show/why-polands-conservative-government-is-causing-alarm-at-the-eu"&gt;Why Poland's Govt. is causing alarm in EU&lt;/a&gt; - PBS&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://bigdoor24.pl/"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Did you know ?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://bigdoor24.pl/"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;BigDoor24.pl sends you a zl. 250 retail voucher of your choice for every successful Polish Mortgage Applicant referred - (in addition to what we send them) - register now for your personal referral code.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Sport&lt;/strong&gt; - &lt;a href="https://www.polskieradio.pl/395/7790/Artykul/2347175,World-Summer-Polonia-Games-open-in-Poland"&gt;Polonia Games kick off &lt;/a&gt;- TheNews&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Odds &amp;amp; Ends&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://kafkadesk.org/2019/07/26/warsaw-buys-fleet-of-electric-buses-in-bid-to-tackle-pollution/"&gt;Electric Bus orders to fight pollution in Warsaw&lt;/a&gt; - Kafkadesk&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Podcast&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Krakcast&lt;/em&gt; - &lt;a href="https://www.krakcast.pl/"&gt;It's holiday time so they are playing the hits&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Have a great Sunday&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Team BigDoor24&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
		<summary>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Today the Shops are OPEN&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</summary>
	</entry>
</feed>